<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: smart_dispute | Rishijeet Mishra | Technologist | Tech Trends & Development Blog]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/smart-dispute/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-10-11T16:55:39+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smartcase Engine: A Modern Framework for Intelligent Case Management]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/smartcase-engine-a-modern-framework-for-intelligent-case-management/"/>
        <updated>2025-05-27T22:54:42+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/smartcase-engine-a-modern-framework-for-intelligent-case-management</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In today&rsquo;s dynamic business environment, efficient case management is paramount. Enter <a href="https://github.com/rishijeet/smartcase-engine">Smartcase Engine</a>, an advanced case management framework designed to streamline complex case handling through real-time tracking, efficient workflows, and automated decision-making processes.</p>

<a name="What-is-Smartcase-Engine-3f-"></a>
<h2>What is Smartcase Engine?</h2>

<p>Smartcase Engine is a modular, microservices-based platform tailored for managing intricate case workflows. It offers:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Real-Time Case Tracking</strong>: Monitor cases as they progress through various stages.</li>
<li><strong>Efficient Workflows</strong>: Automate and optimize the sequence of tasks involved in case resolution.</li>
<li><strong>Automated Decision-Making</strong>: Leverage predefined rules and AI to make informed decisions without manual intervention.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/smartcase_engine.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: <a href="https://github.com/rishijeet/smartcase-engine">Rishijeet Mishra&rsquo;s Blog</a></em></p>

<!--more-->


<a name="Deep-Dive:-Smartcase-Engine-Architecture"></a>
<h2>Deep Dive: Smartcase Engine Architecture</h2>

<p>At the heart of Smartcase Engine is a clean, extensible <strong>microservices-based architecture</strong> designed to support complex workflows in case/dispute management scenarios. The system is broken into discrete services that communicate via REST APIs and Kafka for event-driven interactions. This modular approach allows teams to scale and evolve components independently.</p>

<p>Let’s explore the core services that power this engine:</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Dispute-Intake-Service-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Dispute Intake Service</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>: This is the gateway to the system — the service responsible for accepting new cases or disputes.</p>

<p><strong>Responsibilities</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Receive new dispute cases via API or event (Kafka).</li>
<li>Validate and enrich the incoming payload.</li>
<li>Generate a unique dispute ID.</li>
<li>Store initial metadata and emit an event to kick off downstream workflow.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Technical Highlights</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Built using Java + Quarkus for lightweight runtime.</li>
<li>Connects to Kafka for emitting intake-completed events.</li>
<li>Persists initial data in a database (e.g., PostgreSQL or any pluggable DB).</li>
<li>Implements REST endpoints for manual intake testing or system integration.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why it matters</strong>:
This service ensures that all disputes entering the system are properly structured and immediately traceable — forming the root of all subsequent orchestration.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Dispute-Workflow-Service-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Dispute Workflow Service</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>: This is the <em>brain</em> of the engine, orchestrating the lifecycle of a dispute across multiple business stages.</p>

<p><strong>Responsibilities</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Define and manage the state machine (or BPMN-style flow) for a dispute.</li>
<li>Trigger actions based on status updates (e.g., escalate, resolve, pause).</li>
<li>Call external services when required (e.g., fetch additional metadata, update agent queue).</li>
<li>Track state transitions and support retries/failures.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Technical Highlights</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Uses a stateless orchestration model.</li>
<li>Integration with Kafka allows event-driven step progression.</li>
<li>Could be integrated with BPMN engines (like Camunda or Flowable) for visual modeling.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why it matters</strong>:
This is the system&rsquo;s core engine. It allows Smartcase to define complex, non-linear workflows without hardcoding logic into the intake or agent UI layers.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Dispute-Classification-Service-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Dispute Classification Service</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>: Adds intelligence to the process by classifying disputes into appropriate categories.</p>

<p><strong>Responsibilities</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use business rules or ML models to assign dispute types (e.g., &ldquo;billing error&rdquo;, &ldquo;fraud&rdquo;, &ldquo;product defect&rdquo;).</li>
<li>Optionally flag high-risk or high-priority disputes.</li>
<li>Feed classification results back into the workflow service to route the case accordingly.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Technical Highlights</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Stateless classification service.</li>
<li>Integrates with a basic rule engine or external ML service (could be backed by Python/ONNX, or a local inference server).</li>
<li>Input: structured dispute metadata. Output: classification code or tag.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why it matters</strong>:
Classification drives automation. By programmatically tagging and triaging disputes, Smartcase avoids human bottlenecks and supports intelligent queue assignment.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Agent-UI-Service-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Agent UI Service</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>: The interface between human agents and the system.</p>

<p><strong>Responsibilities</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Display dispute data and current status.</li>
<li>Allow agents to take actions (e.g., approve, reject, escalate).</li>
<li>Show workflow progression.</li>
<li>Track comments, attachments, and communication logs.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Technical Highlights</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Frontend (typically in React or Angular).</li>
<li>Backend proxy or BFF layer in Quarkus serving data via REST.</li>
<li>Authenticated access with role-based views (agent, supervisor, auditor).</li>
<li>Pagination, search, filters, and sort capabilities to handle large volumes.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why it matters</strong>:
No matter how automated the backend is, disputes often need human judgment. This UI is purpose-built for efficiency and transparency in resolution workflows.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Dispute-Common-Module-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Dispute Common Module</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>: A shared library of core utilities and contracts.</p>

<p><strong>Responsibilities</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Define POJOs (Plain Old Java Objects) and DTOs (Data Transfer Objects).</li>
<li>Common validation logic.</li>
<li>Central configuration definitions.</li>
<li>Shared Kafka event schema.</li>
<li>Error handling standards and API response models.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Technical Highlights</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Packaged as a reusable JAR.</li>
<li>Imported by all services as a dependency.</li>
<li>Promotes DRY principles and API consistency.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Why it matters</strong>:
Microservices need to stay loosely coupled — but shared types and utilities must remain consistent. This module enforces a standard language across the ecosystem.</p>

<hr />

<a name="Optional-Add-2d-ons--28-Future-Ready-29-"></a>
<h3>Optional Add-ons (Future Ready)</h3>

<p>Depending on your scale and use case, Smartcase Engine can be extended with:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Notification Service</strong>: For sending SMS/email alerts to users or agents.</li>
<li><strong>Audit Logging</strong>: For compliance with financial or legal audits.</li>
<li><strong>Retry/Dead-letter Queue Mechanism</strong>: To gracefully handle transient failures.</li>
<li><strong>Observability Tools</strong>: Integrated with Prometheus, Grafana, and OpenTelemetry for distributed tracing.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Deployment-and-Setup"></a>
<h2>Deployment and Setup</h2>

<p>Smartcase Engine is containerized using Docker, facilitating seamless deployment. Key scripts and configurations include:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Dockerfile</strong>: Defines the environment for each microservice.</li>
<li><strong>docker-compose.yml</strong>: Orchestrates multi-container deployments for local development and testing.</li>
<li><strong>build-and-deploy.sh</strong>: Automates the build and deployment process.</li>
<li><strong>start-services.sh</strong>: Initiates all services concurrently.</li>
</ul>


<p>To get started:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git clone https://github.com/rishijeet/smartcase-engine.git
cd smartcase-engine
chmod +x build-and-deploy.sh start-services.sh
./build-and-deploy.sh
./start-services.sh
</code></pre>

<a name="Testing-and-Validation"></a>
<h2>Testing and Validation</h2>

<p>Each microservice includes unit and integration tests to ensure reliability. The modular design allows for isolated testing, simplifying debugging and maintenance.</p>

<a name="Potential-Use-Cases"></a>
<h2>Potential Use Cases</h2>

<p>Smartcase Engine&rsquo;s versatility makes it suitable for various domains:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Services</strong>: Automating dispute resolutions in banking and insurance.</li>
<li><strong>Customer Support</strong>: Managing customer complaints and service requests.</li>
<li><strong>Legal Case Management</strong>: Tracking legal cases, evidence, and proceedings.</li>
<li><strong>Healthcare</strong>: Handling patient grievances and administrative cases.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Contributing-to-Smartcase-Engine"></a>
<h2>Contributing to Smartcase Engine</h2>

<p>The project welcomes contributions from the developer community. To contribute:</p>

<ol>
<li>Fork the repository.</li>
<li>Create a new branch for your feature or bugfix.</li>
<li>Ensure code quality by running existing tests and adding new ones if necessary.</li>
<li>Submit a pull request with a clear description of your changes.</li>
</ol>


<a name="Further-Reading"></a>
<h2>Further Reading</h2>

<p>For more in-depth information:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rishijeet/smartcase-engine">Smartcase Engine GitHub Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/microservices.html">Microservices Architecture</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.docker.com/">Docker Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.omg.org/bpmn/">BPMN Standards</a></li>
</ul>


<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Smartcase Engine exemplifies how modern architectural principles can be harnessed to build robust, scalable, and efficient case management systems. Whether you&rsquo;re looking to streamline dispute resolutions or manage complex workflows, Smartcase Engine offers a solid foundation to build upon.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
