<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: social | Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/social/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2024-01-14T01:15:13+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blockchain - Really worth in elections ?]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/blockchain-really-worth-in-elections/"/>
        <updated>2017-05-12T10:37:14+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/blockchain-really-worth-in-elections</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Issues with <strong>EVM ( Electronic Voting Machine )</strong> have been the talk of the town for quite a while in India nowadays. Political parties have been taking about going back to voting mechanism using ballot boxes, wherein there would be very less possibility of non-legitimate voting. EVMs are prone to hacking, untrusted votes, digital errors as explained by these political parties.</p>

<p>I ask you political parties this, why ballot boxes or directly &ldquo;why papers&rdquo; ? Why cut trees to achieve your goal considering the fact that, we are living in the - digital era with brilliant minds across the country to make things possible using technology.</p>

<p>The recent government (people too) has been keen towards its programme of Digital India.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>As the website says -</p>

<p><em>The Digital India programme is a flagship programme of the Government of India with a vision to transform India into a digitally empowered society and knowledge economy.</em></p>

<p>So why paper for casting votes ?</p>

<p>The question is - Can the blockchain technology solve this problem ?</p>

<p>The answer to the question is - Yes</p>

<p>Adopting to the Blockchain technology will not only ensure, that the vote casted is trusted but will also eradicate the underlying issues of hacking, third party dependency, voting transactions, fraud &amp; other securities hacks.</p>

<p>Importantly it will reduce the cost of elections drastically and the government could utilise its funds in other major projects. Note, the Loksabha election 2014 costed around <strong>3,500 crore</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/myimages/voting_places.png" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>Simple mechanism to understand this from blockchain perspective.</p>

<ul>
<li>Voting could be casted from any place on a particular day. This could be translated as <strong>NODES</strong> in blockchain.</li>
<li>Voting done at nodes could be validated by a elected nodes or electoral offices. This translates to <strong>MINERS</strong> in blockchain.</li>
<li>Elected nodes or electoral offices would update their transactions. This translates to <strong>SYNCHRONISATION</strong> ledger in blockchain.</li>
<li>Transactions are up to date at any electoral offices and results could be declared instantly on the same day if required.</li>
</ul>


<p>Government should just ensure the infrastructure is developed for this and is prioritise.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s all participate in making India a - <strong>Digital India</strong></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
