<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2023-05-22T19:00:41+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
    </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unleashing the Power of AI Transformer: Revolutionizing Artificial Intelligence]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/unleashing-the-power-of-ai-transformer-revolutionizing-artificial-intelligence/"/>
        <updated>2023-05-22T18:57:12+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/unleashing-the-power-of-ai-transformer-revolutionizing-artificial-intelligence</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, the field of artificial intelligence (AI) has witnessed a groundbreaking advancement with the introduction of the AI Transformer model. Inspired by the Transformer architecture, which gained fame for its effectiveness in natural language processing tasks, the AI Transformer has emerged as a powerful tool that revolutionizes various domains, including language translation, image recognition, and speech synthesis. In this blog, we will explore the capabilities and impact of the AI Transformer model, shedding light on its remarkable contributions to the world of AI.</p>

<h5>Understanding the Transformer Architecture</h5>

<p>The Transformer architecture, initially introduced for machine translation tasks, reshaped the landscape of AI. Unlike traditional recurrent neural networks (RNNs) or convolutional neural networks (CNNs), the Transformer model leverages a self-attention mechanism, enabling it to capture global dependencies in the input data efficiently. This architecture eliminates the need for sequential processing and allows for parallelization, resulting in faster and more accurate predictions.</p>

<h5>Language Translation Advancements</h5>

<p>One of the key applications of the AI Transformer is language translation. With its ability to handle long-range dependencies and capture contextual information effectively, the AI Transformer has significantly improved the quality of machine translation systems. The model&rsquo;s attention mechanism enables it to attend to relevant parts of the input text, producing more accurate and coherent translations across different languages. This breakthrough has bridged communication gaps and fostered cross-cultural understanding on a global scale.</p>

<h5>Image Recognition and Computer Vision</h5>

<p>The impact of the AI Transformer extends beyond natural language processing. In the realm of computer vision, the model has demonstrated remarkable performance in image recognition tasks. By leveraging the self-attention mechanism, the AI Transformer can analyze and interpret complex visual data, leading to more accurate object detection, image segmentation, and scene understanding. This has paved the way for advancements in autonomous vehicles, robotics, medical imaging, and various other industries reliant on computer vision technologies.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h5>Speech Synthesis and Natural Language Generation</h5>

<p>Another domain where the AI Transformer has left an indelible mark is speech synthesis and natural language generation. By leveraging its ability to learn dependencies and patterns in sequential data, the AI Transformer can generate human-like speech and produce coherent and contextually relevant text. This has found applications in voice assistants, audiobooks, accessibility technologies, and more, enhancing the overall user experience and accessibility of information.</p>

<h5>Challenges and Future Directions</h5>

<p>While the AI Transformer has achieved remarkable success, there are still challenges to overcome. The model&rsquo;s immense computational requirements and memory constraints can pose difficulties for real-time and resource-limited applications. Researchers are continuously exploring techniques to optimize and compress the AI Transformer, enabling its deployment on edge devices and enhancing its efficiency.</p>

<p>The future of the AI Transformer holds tremendous promise. As advancements continue, we can expect the model to tackle more complex tasks, push the boundaries of AI capabilities, and facilitate breakthroughs in areas such as drug discovery, personalized medicine, recommendation systems, and intelligent virtual assistants.</p>

<h5>Conclusion</h5>

<p>The AI Transformer has emerged as a game-changer in the field of artificial intelligence. Its ability to capture long-range dependencies and understand context has revolutionized language translation, image recognition, speech synthesis, and natural language generation. As we delve deeper into the potential of the AI Transformer, we can anticipate transformative advancements across various domains, propelling us toward a future where AI seamlessly integrates into our daily lives.</p>

<p>Through continued research and development, the AI Transformer will undoubtedly contribute to the evolution of AI, driving innovation and enhancing the way we interact with technology. Brace yourself for a future where the power of the AI Transformer shapes the world as we know it.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Dynamic Web Applications with React and Firebase]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/building-dynamic-web-applications-with-react-and-firebase/"/>
        <updated>2023-05-22T13:22:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/building-dynamic-web-applications-with-react-and-firebase</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years, React has emerged as a popular JavaScript library for building user interfaces, while Firebase has become a powerful platform for developing and deploying web applications. When combined, React and Firebase provide developers with a robust toolkit for creating dynamic and real-time web applications. In this blog, we will explore the integration of React and Firebase, highlighting the benefits and demonstrating how they work seamlessly together.</p>

<h4>An Overview of React and Firebase</h4>

<p>React is a JavaScript library developed by Facebook, designed to build reusable and interactive user interfaces. It follows a component-based architecture that allows developers to create modular and reusable UI elements, making it easier to manage complex web applications.</p>

<p>Firebase, on the other hand, is a comprehensive platform developed by Google for building web and mobile applications. It offers a wide range of services, including real-time database, authentication, hosting, cloud functions, and more. Firebase simplifies the backend infrastructure, enabling developers to focus on the frontend development and user experience.</p>

<h4>Setting Up a React App with Firebase</h4>

<p>To get started with React and Firebase, you&rsquo;ll need to set up a React project and integrate Firebase into it. This involves creating a new React app using tools like Create React App and configuring Firebase SDKs and authentication methods. Once set up, you can leverage Firebase services within your React components, making API calls, handling user authentication, and storing data.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Real-time Data Synchronization with Firebase Realtime Database</h4>

<p>Firebase Realtime Database is a NoSQL cloud database that allows you to store and synchronize data in real-time across multiple clients. With React, you can seamlessly integrate Firebase Realtime Database to create real-time collaborative applications, chat applications, live dashboards, and more. React&rsquo;s state management and Firebase&rsquo;s real-time synchronization capabilities work together to provide a smooth and responsive user experience.</p>

<h4>User Authentication with Firebase Authentication</h4>

<p>Firebase Authentication provides an easy-to-use authentication system that allows users to sign up, sign in, and manage their accounts securely. React can leverage Firebase Authentication to implement features like user registration, login, password reset, and social media authentication within your application. React&rsquo;s component-driven approach can help create a seamless and intuitive user interface for handling authentication flows.</p>

<h4>Deploying React Apps with Firebase Hosting</h4>

<p>Once your React app is ready, Firebase Hosting enables you to deploy your application with ease. It provides a fast and secure hosting solution for your static assets, including HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and other resources. Firebase Hosting also supports features like custom domains, SSL certificates, and automatic deployments, simplifying the process of launching your React app to the web.</p>

<h4>Cloud Functions and Serverless Computing</h4>

<p>Firebase Cloud Functions allows you to extend the functionality of your React app by running server-side code in a serverless environment. With Cloud Functions, you can perform server-side operations, process data, trigger events, and integrate with other services. React components can interact with Cloud Functions to offload heavy computation or perform backend tasks asynchronously.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>React and Firebase provide a powerful combination for building dynamic and real-time web applications. React&rsquo;s component-driven architecture, along with Firebase&rsquo;s suite of services for data storage, authentication, hosting, and more, enables developers to create modern, responsive, and feature-rich web applications with ease. By leveraging the capabilities of React and Firebase, developers can focus on delivering exceptional user experiences while minimizing the complexity of backend infrastructure development. Whether you&rsquo;re building a small project or a large-scale application, the React-Firebase duo offers a comprehensive toolkit to bring your ideas to life.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web 3.0 - How does it impacts IOT ?]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/web-3-dot-0-how-does-it-impacts-iot/"/>
        <updated>2023-05-22T13:13:54+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/web-3-dot-0-how-does-it-impacts-iot</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Web 3.0 has a significant impact on the Internet of Things (IoT) by enhancing its capabilities, security, and interoperability. Here are some key ways in which Web 3.0 transforms the IoT landscape:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Decentralized Data Management: Web 3.0 leverages blockchain technology to create decentralized data marketplaces and storage solutions. This allows IoT devices to securely and autonomously store and exchange data without relying on centralized servers or intermediaries. Decentralization increases data privacy and reduces the risk of data breaches.</p></li>
<li><p>Enhanced Security and Privacy: With Web 3.0, IoT devices can leverage blockchain&rsquo;s cryptographic techniques to establish secure communication channels and ensure data integrity. By eliminating single points of failure and relying on consensus mechanisms, Web 3.0 provides a more robust security framework for IoT devices, mitigating risks associated with hacking, tampering, and unauthorized access.</p></li>
<li><p>Interoperability and Standardization: Web 3.0 fosters interoperability among diverse IoT devices and platforms. By utilizing decentralized protocols and standards, Web 3.0 enables seamless communication and data exchange between different IoT devices and ecosystems. This interoperability unlocks new possibilities for cross-domain collaborations, creating a more connected and efficient IoT ecosystem.</p></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p>Autonomous Device-to-Device Transactions: Web 3.0, powered by smart contracts, enables autonomous transactions between IoT devices. Devices can negotiate and execute agreements based on predefined conditions, eliminating the need for intermediaries. For example, smart contracts can enable devices to autonomously manage energy consumption, negotiate pricing, or perform self-maintenance tasks, enhancing the efficiency and automation of IoT networks.</p></li>
<li><p>Monetization of IoT Data: Web 3.0 introduces decentralized data marketplaces, where IoT device owners can securely and transparently monetize their data. Through blockchain-based platforms, device-generated data can be tokenized, allowing users to retain ownership and control over their data while selling or sharing it with interested parties. This opens up new revenue streams and incentives for IoT device owners.</p></li>
<li><p>Edge Computing and Reduced Latency: Web 3.0 leverages edge computing to process and analyze IoT data at the network edge, closer to the devices generating the data. This reduces latency and enables real-time decision-making, making IoT applications more responsive and efficient. Edge computing also reduces the reliance on centralized cloud servers, improving scalability and reliability in IoT deployments.</p></li>
<li><p>Trust and Accountability: Web 3.0&rsquo;s transparent and immutable nature, powered by blockchain, enhances trust and accountability in the IoT ecosystem. Device behavior and data transactions can be recorded on the blockchain, creating an auditable and tamper-proof record. This fosters trust among stakeholders and enables better accountability in areas such as supply chain management, autonomous vehicles, and healthcare.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>In conclusion, Web 3.0 revolutionizes the Internet of Things by providing a decentralized, secure, and interoperable framework. It enhances data privacy, enables autonomous transactions, fosters trust, and unlocks new opportunities for monetization and collaboration. Web 3.0&rsquo;s integration with IoT promises a more connected, efficient, and trustworthy future for smart devices and applications.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web 3.0 - Decentralizing Internet]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/web-3-dot-0-decentralizing-internet/"/>
        <updated>2022-10-29T22:04:22+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/web-3-dot-0-decentralizing-internet</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet has become an integral part of our lives, transforming the way we communicate, work, and access information. From the early days of Web 1.0, where static websites provided basic information, to the dynamic and interactive Web 2.0 era that brought social media, online collaboration, and user-generated content, the Internet has continuously evolved. Now, a new paradigm shift is on the horizon - Web 3.0. In this blog, we will explore the exciting possibilities and potential of Web 3.0, a decentralized and user-centric vision of the future internet.</p>

<ul>
<li>Defining Web 3.0: Decentralization and Interoperability</li>
</ul>


<p>Web 3.0, often referred to as the &ldquo;Decentralized Web,&rdquo; represents a departure from the centralized systems that dominate the current internet landscape. It is built on principles of decentralization, interoperability, and enhanced user control. Unlike Web 2.0, which relies heavily on centralized platforms and intermediaries, Web 3.0 envisions a distributed network where users have greater ownership and control over their data and digital identities.</p>

<ul>
<li>Blockchain Technology: The Backbone of Web 3.0</li>
</ul>


<p>At the core of Web 3.0 lies blockchain technology, the decentralized ledger system that underpins cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum. Blockchain provides a transparent, tamper-proof, and secure way to record and verify digital transactions. With Web 3.0, blockchain expands its scope beyond financial applications, enabling the development of decentralized applications (dApps), smart contracts, and decentralized autonomous organizations (DAOs).</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>Decentralized Applications (dApps): Empowering Users</li>
</ul>


<p>Web 3.0 empowers users by placing them at the center of the internet experience. Decentralized applications (dApps) are one of the cornerstones of Web 3.0, offering users greater control, privacy, and ownership of their data. dApps leverage blockchain&rsquo;s decentralized nature to eliminate middlemen, reduce censorship, and enable direct peer-to-peer interactions. These applications span various domains, including finance, healthcare, supply chain management, and social media.</p>

<ul>
<li>Smart Contracts: Trust and Automation</li>
</ul>


<p>Smart contracts, powered by blockchain technology, are self-executing agreements that automatically enforce the terms and conditions encoded within them. Web 3.0 leverages smart contracts to facilitate trust and automation in a wide range of transactions. These contracts eliminate the need for intermediaries, reducing costs, increasing efficiency, and ensuring transparency. Smart contracts have the potential to revolutionize industries such as real estate, insurance, and intellectual property rights.</p>

<ul>
<li>Enhanced Privacy and Security</li>
</ul>


<p>Web 3.0 addresses growing concerns about data privacy and security. By leveraging decentralized systems and cryptographic techniques, Web 3.0 offers enhanced privacy protection. Users have greater control over their personal information, deciding when and how it is shared. Moreover, the decentralized nature of Web 3.0 reduces the risk of data breaches and single points of failure, enhancing overall security and resilience.</p>

<ul>
<li>The Internet of Things (IoT) in Web 3.0</li>
</ul>


<p>Web 3.0 integrates the Internet of Things (IoT) into its fabric, enabling seamless connectivity and communication between devices.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rest API with Go &amp; Gorilla Mux]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/rest-api-with-go-and-gorilla-mux/"/>
        <updated>2021-02-20T23:12:49+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/rest-api-with-go-and-gorilla-mux</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gorilla is a web toolkit for the Go programming language. The gorilla/mux implements a request router and dispatcher for matching incomings requests to the respective handlers.</p>

<p>One of the cool feature it has is that the registered URLs can be built or reversed which helps maintaining the references to resources and nested routes are only tested if the parent route matches. This is useful to define groups of routes that share common conditions like a host, a path prefix or other repeated attributes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The routes can be declared as mentioned below</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='go'><span class='line'><span class="kd">func</span> <span class="nx">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">r</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="nx">mux</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewRouter</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HandleFunc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">HomeHandler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HandleFunc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/users&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">UsersHandler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HandleFunc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/blogs&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">BlogHandler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Handle</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The basic http server code</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='go'><span class='line'><span class="c1">// Author: Rishijeet Mishra</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kn">package</span> <span class="nx">main</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="p">(</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s">&quot;net/http&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s">&quot;encoding/json&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s">&quot;log&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="s">&quot;github.com/gorilla/mux&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">func</span> <span class="nx">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">router</span> <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="nx">mux</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewRouter</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Routes consist of a path and a handler function.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">router</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HandleFunc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/myhandler&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">MyHandler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Bind to a port and pass our router in</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">log</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Fatal</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ListenAndServe</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;:5000&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">router</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">func</span> <span class="nx">MyHandler</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span> <span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ResponseWriter</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">r</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Request</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">//w.Write([]byte(&quot;The page to be rendered&quot;))</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Header</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">Set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Content-Type&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&quot;application/json&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">json</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewEncoder</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">Encode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">struct</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nx">key</span> <span class="kt">string</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="s">&quot;value&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">}</span> <span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let&rsquo;s add the POST method</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='go'><span class='line'><span class="c1">// Add the route</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">HandleFunc</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/add/{item}&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">addItem</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">Methods</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;POST&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">//Add the func</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">func</span> <span class="nx">addItem</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span> <span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ResponseWriter</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">r</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Request</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">itemholder</span>  <span class="o">:=</span> <span class="nx">mux</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Vars</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">)[</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="nx">item</span><span class="err">&#39;</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">data</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nb">append</span><span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">itemholder</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">json</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewEncoder</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">Encode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let&rsquo;s add the GET</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='go'><span class='line'><span class="c1">// The struct for grouping</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">type</span> <span class="nx">Item</span> <span class="kd">struct</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">Data</span> <span class="kt">string</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">data</span> <span class="p">[]</span><span class="nx">Item</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="p">[]</span><span class="nx">Item</span><span class="p">{}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">func</span> <span class="nx">addItem</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span> <span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">ResponseWriter</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">r</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="nx">http</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Request</span><span class="p">){</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">latestItem</span> <span class="nx">Item</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">json</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewDecoder</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">r</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Body</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">Decode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">latestItem</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">data</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nb">append</span><span class="p">(</span> <span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">latestItem</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// output the json</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">Header</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">Set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;Content-Type&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&quot;application/json&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">json</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">NewEncoder</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">w</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">Encode</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">data</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Mux supports the addition of middlewares to a Router, which are executed in the order they are added if a match is found, including its subrouters. Middlewares are (typically) small pieces of code which take one request, do something with it, and pass it down to another middleware or the final handler.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='batch'><span class='line'>type MiddlewareFunc func(http.Handler) http.Handler
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">//Add</span> the middleware to the route
</span><span class='line'>r :<span class="o">=</span> mux.NewRouter()
</span><span class='line'>r.HandleFunc(<span class="s2">&quot;/&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> handler)
</span><span class='line'>r.Use(loggingMiddleware)
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Click for more details on the <a href="https://github.com/gorilla/mux">gorilla/mux</a></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tuning Apache Kafka’s performance]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/tuning-apache-kafkas-performance/"/>
        <updated>2019-07-11T11:42:32+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/tuning-apache-kafkas-performance</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, Apache Kafka is one of the best pub-sub messaging system used widely across several technology’s based industries. Originated at LinkedIn and was open sourced in early 2011.</p>

<p>Ok, so what so special about <strong>Apache Kafka</strong> ? Here are the few things Kafka is meant to handle.</p>

<ul>
<li>High throughput to support large volume event feeds.</li>
<li>Real time processing of enormous amount of data.</li>
<li>Support large data backlogs to handle periodic ingestion from offline systems.</li>
<li>Support low - latency delivery of the messages compared to other messaging systems</li>
<li>High Availability, Fault Tolerance.</li>
</ul>


<p>So what else are you looking ?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Now if you know about Apache Kafka a bit, here are few things we can fine tune to make it better in terms of performance. Let’s categories the system into the following aspects and see what could be done in each space.</p>

<ul>
<li>Producers</li>
<li>Brokers</li>
<li>Consumers</li>
</ul>


<h2>Producers</h2>

<h3>Asynchronous</h3>

<p>Now think, how long you want to wait for the ack on the message sent to the broker ? Answer to this question will change the speed of handling the messages in the Kafka.</p>

<p>request.required.acks is the property of the producer.</p>

<p>Possible values for this are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>0</code> = producer never waits for the ack from the broker. This will give you “Least durability and least latency”.</li>
<li><code>1</code> = producer gets ack from the master replica. This will give you “some durability and less latency”.</li>
<li><code>-1</code> = producer gets ack from the all the replicas. This will give you “most durability and most latency”.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Batching</h3>

<p>How about batching the messages ? Let’s use the asynchronous producers.</p>

<p><code>producer.type=1</code> to make the producers run async.</p>

<p>You can get the “callback” for the messages here to know their status. Now batch your messages to the brokers in different threads, this will improve the throughput. Some configuration to handle the messages in this scenario are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>queue.buffer.max.ms</code> - Duration of the batch window.</li>
<li><code>batch.num.messages</code> - Number of messages to be sent in a batch.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Compression</h3>

<p>Use the compression property to reduces the I/O on the machine. We might also want to think of the CPU load when it decompresses the message object back. So, maintain a balance between the two. compression.codec - Values are none, gzip and snappy</p>

<p>For presumably large messages say - 10G , you might want to pass the file location of the share drive in the maessage rather than the payload itself. This would be tremendously faster.</p>

<h3>Timeout</h3>

<p>Don’t wait for the message unnecessarily unless its is really really required. Have a “timeout”</p>

<p><code>request.timeout.ms</code> - The time until the broker waits before sending error back to the client.
Amount of time to block before dropping the messages when running in async mode ( default = indefinitely )</p>

<h2>Brokers</h2>

<h3>Partition</h3>

<p>Plan to have as number of partitions = number of consumers. This will increase the concurrency, the more the partitions the more the concurrency. Remember, more the partitions more the latency too. Also, recommended to have one partition per physical disk to ensure I/O is not the bottleneck while writing the logs.</p>

<p>Use “kafka-reassign-partitions.sh” to ensure partition is not overloaded.</p>

<p>Some of the configurations worth mentioning here are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>num.io.threads</code> - The number of I/O threads server uses to execute the requests.</li>
<li><code>num.partitions</code> - Number of partitions per topic</li>
<li><code>log.flush.interval,messages</code> - The number of messages written to the log partition before we force an fsync on the log.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Consumers</h2>

<p>The max number of consumers for the topic is equal to number of partitions. Have enough partitions to handle all the consumers in your Kafka’s ecosystem.</p>

<p>Consumer in the same consumer group split the partitions among themselves. Adding more consumers to a group can enhance performance.</p>

<p>Performance is not affected by adding more consumer groups</p>

<p><code>replica.high.watermark.checkpoint.interval.ms</code> can affect the throughput. When reading from partition, you can mark the last point where you read the information. If you set checkpoint watermark for every event, you will have high durability but hit on the performance. Rather, set it to check the offset for every x number of messages wherein you have margin of safety and will less impact your throughput.</p>

<h3>Timeout</h3>

<p>Choose the timeouts and onward pipeline properly. Also, refer to Apache Kafka doc for setting fetch size, time, auto-commit etc.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blockchain - Really worth in elections ?]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/blockchain-really-worth-in-elections/"/>
        <updated>2017-05-12T10:37:14+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/blockchain-really-worth-in-elections</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Issues with <strong>EVM ( Electronic Voting Machine )</strong> have been the talk of the town for quite a while in India nowadays. Political parties have been taking about going back to voting mechanism using ballot boxes, wherein there would be very less possibility of non-legitimate voting. EVMs are prone to hacking, untrusted votes, digital errors as explained by these political parties.</p>

<p>I ask you political parties this, why ballot boxes or directly &ldquo;why papers&rdquo; ? Why cut trees to achieve your goal considering the fact that, we are living in the - digital era with brilliant minds across the country to make things possible using technology.</p>

<p>The recent government (people too) has been keen towards its programme of Digital India.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>As the website says -</p>

<p><em>The Digital India programme is a flagship programme of the Government of India with a vision to transform India into a digitally empowered society and knowledge economy.</em></p>

<p>So why paper for casting votes ?</p>

<p>The question is - Can the blockchain technology solve this problem ?</p>

<p>The answer to the question is - Yes</p>

<p>Adopting to the Blockchain technology will not only ensure, that the vote casted is trusted but will also eradicate the underlying issues of hacking, third party dependency, voting transactions, fraud &amp; other securities hacks.</p>

<p>Importantly it will reduce the cost of elections drastically and the government could utilise its funds in other major projects. Note, the Loksabha election 2014 costed around <strong>3,500 crore</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://rishijeet.github.io/images/myimages/voting_places.png" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>Simple mechanism to understand this from blockchain perspective.</p>

<ul>
<li>Voting could be casted from any place on a particular day. This could be translated as <strong>NODES</strong> in blockchain.</li>
<li>Voting done at nodes could be validated by a elected nodes or electoral offices. This translates to <strong>MINERS</strong> in blockchain.</li>
<li>Elected nodes or electoral offices would update their transactions. This translates to <strong>SYNCHRONISATION</strong> ledger in blockchain.</li>
<li>Transactions are up to date at any electoral offices and results could be declared instantly on the same day if required.</li>
</ul>


<p>Government should just ensure the infrastructure is developed for this and is prioritise.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s all participate in making India a - <strong>Digital India</strong></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fancybox2 to Fancybox3 for image gallery]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/fancybox2-to-fancybox3-for-image-gallery/"/>
        <updated>2017-05-12T09:58:37+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/fancybox2-to-fancybox3-for-image-gallery</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently migrated my image gallery to Fancybox3 from Fancybox2. Fancybox3 has some of the advantages over its previous version.
The important one I like is the fact that you have to code less.</p>

<ul>
<li>Import the javascript</li>
<li>Wrap the images with class and the work is done.</li>
<li>It supports the image security too. <i class="em em---1"></i>
<!-- more --></li>
</ul>


<p>Personally, I like the masonry style more and working on moving towards its soon. Still exploring the feasibility.
The details on the masonry grid could be found <a href="https://masonry.desandro.com/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Did you notice the masonry grid used in <a href="http://iam.beyonce.com/tagged/my_work">Beyonce&rsquo;s Website</a> ? <i class="em em-blush"></i></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distributed Computing - Quorum]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/distributed-computing/"/>
        <updated>2016-09-04T18:40:02+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/distributed-computing</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a distributed database system, a transaction could be executing its operations at multiple sites. Since atomicity requires every distributed transaction to be atomic, the transaction must have the same fate (commit or abort) at every site. In case of network partitioning, sites are partitioned and the partitions may not be able to communicate with each other. This is where a quorum-based technique comes in. The fundamental idea is that a transaction is executed if the majority of sites vote to execute it.</p>

<h4>Quorum Consensus Protocol</h4>

<p>This is one of the distributed lock manager based concurrency control protocol in distributed database systems. It works as follows;</p>

<ul>
<li>The protocol assigns each site that have a replica with a weight.</li>
<li>For any data item, the protocol assigns a read quorum Qr and write quorum Qw. Here, Qr and Qw are two integers (sum of weights of some sites). And, these two integers are chosen according to the following conditions put together;</li>
</ul>


<p><code>Qr + Qw &gt; S - rule which avoids read-write conflict. (i.e, two transactions cannot read and write concurrently)</code></p>

<p><code>2 * Qw &gt; S - rule which avoids write-write conflict. (i.e, two transactions cannot write concurrently)</code></p>

<p>Here, S is the total weight of all sites in which the data item replicated.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>How do we perform read and write on replicas?</h4>

<ul>
<li>A transaction that needs a data item for reading purpose has to lock enough sites. ie, it has lock sites with the sum of their weight >= Qr. Read quorum must always intersect with write quorum.</li>
<li>A transaction that needs a data item for writing purpose has to lock enough sites. ie, it has lock sites with the sum of their weight >= Qw.</li>
</ul>


<h4>How does it work?</h4>

<p>Let us assume a fully replicated distributed database with four sites S1, S2, S3, and S4.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>According to the protocol, we need to assign a weight to every site. (This weight can be chosen on many factors like the availability of the site, latency etc.). For simplicity, let us assume the weight as 1 for all sites.</p></li>
<li><p>Let us choose the values for Qr and Qw as 2 and 3. Our total weight S is 4. And according to the conditions, our Qr and Qw values are correct;
<br>
<code>Qr + Qw &gt; S =&gt; 2 + 3 &gt; 4               True</code>
<br>
<code>2 * Qw  &gt; S =&gt; 2 * 3 &gt; 4               True</code>
<br></p></li>
<li>Now, a transaction which needs a read lock on a data item has to lock 2 sites. A transaction which needs a write lock on data item has to lock 3 sites.</li>
</ol>


<h6>Case 1<code>&sup1;</code></h6>

<p>Read Quorum Qr = 2, Write Quorum Qw = 3, Site’s weight = 1, Total weight of sites S = 4</p>

<ul>
<li>Read Lock

<ol>
<li>Read request has to lock at least two replicas (2 sites in our example)</li>
<li>Any two sites can be locked</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Write Lock

<ol>
<li>Write request has to lock at least three replicas (3 sites in our example)</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>


<h6>Case 2</h6>

<p>Read Quorum Qr = 1, Write Quorum Qw = 4, Site’s weight = 1, Total weight of sites S = 4</p>

<ul>
<li>Read Lock

<ol>
<li>Read lock requires one site</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Write Lock

<ol>
<li>Write lock requires 4 sites</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>


<p><em><code>&sup1;</code>Points and example taken from web.</em></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Microsoft biased towards Linux]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/is-microsoft-biased-towards-linux/"/>
        <updated>2016-03-11T09:45:09+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/is-microsoft-biased-towards-linux</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I see news about Microsoft crafted a switch OS on Debian Linux platform,  announcing its SQL server of Linux and may be some more. Though this is a surprising news as Microsoft windows has released its best OS so far, which is more stable and fast compare to its ancestors, so what could be the reason to move towards Linux is a question. Is this related to the security aspect of the operating system or is it the open source nature of the platform and the community support it has or is it just the recent decision to move towards it ? Whatever it is, I see this as a strong move towards making its environment and platform more robust and performant.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>According to the Microsoft&rsquo;s Blog</p>

<p><i>
These improvements, and many more, are all built into SQL Server and bring you not just a new database but a complete platform for data management, business analytics and intelligent apps – one that can be used in a consistent way across both on-premises and the cloud. In fact, over the last year we’ve been using the SQL Server 2016 code-base to run in production more than 1.4 million SQL Databases in the cloud using our Azure SQL Database as a Service offering, and this real-world experience has made SQL Server 2016 an incredibly robust and battle-hardened data platform.
</i></p>


<p>
As the executive tells the New York Times, this is all about &#8220;market expansion.&#8221; Microsoft would rather corner the server software space, which has been shifting toward Linux, than insist on a Windows-only policy out of stubborn pride. It&#8217;s tough to know if the Linux server crowd will warm up to its longtime arch-rival, but those more open-minded firms are now free to integrate Microsoft without making a wholesale switch.
</p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Memory Management in Python]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/memory-management-in-python/"/>
        <updated>2015-04-22T09:54:01+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/memory-management-in-python</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I came across the interesting write up somewhere on website on memory management in Python. Here are some data facts
which I liked,</p>

<p>Python allocates memory transparently, manages objects using a reference count system, and frees memory when an object’s reference count falls to zero. In theory, it’s swell. In practice, you need to know a few things about Python memory management to get a memory-efficient program running. One of the things you should know, or at least get a good feel about, is the sizes of basic Python objects. Another thing is how Python manages its memory internally.</p>

<p>So let us begin with the size of basic objects. In Python, there’s not a lot of primitive data types: there are ints, longs (an unlimited precision version of ints), floats (which are doubles), tuples, strings, lists, dictionaries, and classes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What is the size of int? A programmer with a C or C++ background will probably guess that the size of a machine-specific int is something like 32 bits, maybe 64; and that therefore it occupies at most 8 bytes. But is that so in Python?</p>

<p>Let us first write a function that shows the sizes of objects (recursively if necessary):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">sys</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">level</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">print</span> <span class="s">&quot;</span><span class="se">\t</span><span class="s">&quot;</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">level</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">__class__</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sys</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">getsizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">x</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nb">hasattr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;__iter__&#39;</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="nb">hasattr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;items&#39;</span><span class="p">):</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">xx</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">items</span><span class="p">():</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">xx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">level</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">else</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">xx</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">:</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">xx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">level</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>We can now use the function to inspect the sizes of the different basic data types:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">63</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">102947298469128649161972364837164</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">918659326943756134897561304875610348756384756193485761304875613948576297485698417</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="c">#If you have a 32-bit 2.7x Python, you’ll see:</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">8</span> <span class="bp">None</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">12</span> <span class="mi">3</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">22</span> <span class="mi">9223372036854775808</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">28</span> <span class="mi">102947298469128649161972364837164</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">48</span> <span class="mi">918659326943756134897561304875610348756384756193485761304875613948576297485698417</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#and if you have a 64-bit 2.7x Python, you’ll see:</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">16</span> <span class="bp">None</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">24</span> <span class="mi">3</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">36</span> <span class="mi">9223372036854775808</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">40</span> <span class="mi">102947298469128649161972364837164</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">60</span> <span class="mi">918659326943756134897561304875610348756384756193485761304875613948576297485698417</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let us focus on the 64-bit version (mainly because that’s what we need the most often in our case). None takes 16 bytes. int takes 24 bytes, three times as much memory as a C int64_t, despite being some kind of “machine-friendly” integer. Long integers (unbounded precision), used to represent integers larger than 263-1, have a minimum size of 36 bytes. Then it grows linearly in the logarithm of the integer represented.</p>

<p>Python’s floats are implementation-specific but seem to be C doubles. However, they do not eat up only 8 bytes:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">3.14159265358979323846264338327950288</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># Output</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">16</span> <span class="mf">3.14159265359</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#on a 32-bit platform and</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">24</span> <span class="mf">3.14159265359</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#on a 64-bit platform.</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That’s again, three times the size a C programmer would expect. Now, what about strings?</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;My hovercraft is full of eels&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>outputs, on a 32 bit platform:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="mi">21</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">50</span> <span class="n">My</span> <span class="n">hovercraft</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="n">full</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">eels</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>and</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="mi">37</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">66</span> <span class="n">My</span> <span class="n">hovercraft</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="n">full</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">eels</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>An empty string costs 37 bytes in a 64-bit environment! Memory used by string then linearly grows in the length of the (useful) string.</p>

<p>Other structures commonly used, tuples, lists, and dictionaries are worthwhile to examine. Lists (which are implemented as array lists, not as linked lists, with everything it entails) are arrays of references to Python objects, allowing them to be heterogeneous. Let us look at our sizes:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">([])</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&quot;toaster&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">230.1</span><span class="p">])</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#outputs</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">32</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">44</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;toaster&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">230.1</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#on a 32-bit platform and</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">72</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">96</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;toaster&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mf">230.1</span><span class="p">]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#on a 64-bit platform. </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>An empty list eats up 72 bytes. The size of an empty, 64-bit C++ std::list() is only 16 bytes,
 4-5 times less. What about tuples? (and dictionaries?):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">({})</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">show_sizeof</span><span class="p">({</span><span class="s">&#39;a&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mi">213</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;b&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mi">2131</span><span class="p">})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>outputs, on a 32-bit box</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="mi">136</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="mi">136</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="s">&#39;a&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">213</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;b&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">2131</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="mi">32</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;a&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">213</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">22</span> <span class="n">a</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">12</span> <span class="mi">213</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="mi">32</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;b&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2131</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">22</span> <span class="n">b</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">12</span> <span class="mi">2131</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="ow">and</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">280</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="mi">280</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="s">&#39;a&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">213</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">&#39;b&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mi">2131</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="mi">72</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;a&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">213</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">38</span> <span class="n">a</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">24</span> <span class="mi">213</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="mi">72</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;b&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2131</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">38</span> <span class="n">b</span>
</span><span class='line'>                <span class="mi">24</span> <span class="mi">2131</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>for a 64-bit box.</p>

<p>This last example is particularly interesting because it “doesn’t add up.” If we look at individual key/value pairs, they take 72 bytes (while their components take 38+24=62 bytes, leaving 10 bytes for the pair itself), but the dictionary takes 280 bytes (rather than a strict minimum of 144=72×2 bytes). The dictionary is supposed to be an efficient data structure for search and the two likely implementations will use more space that strictly necessary. If it’s some kind of tree, then we should pay the cost of internal nodes that contain a key and two pointers to children nodes; if it’s a hash table, then we must have some room with free entries to ensure good performance.</p>

<p>The (somewhat) equivalent <code>std::map</code> C++ structure takes 48 bytes when created (that is,
empty). An empty C++ string takes 8 bytes (then allocated size grows linearly the size of the string). An integer takes 4 bytes (32 bits).</p>

<p>Why does all this matter? It seems that whether an empty string takes 8 bytes or 37 doesn’t change anything much
. That’s true. That’s true until you need to scale. Then, you need to be really careful about how many objects you
create to limit the quantity of memory your program uses. It is a problem in real-life applications. However, to devise a really good strategy about memory management, we must not only consider the sizes of objects, but how many and in which order they are created. It turns out to be very important for Python programs. One key element to understand is how Python allocates its memory internally, which we will discuss next.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[VMware Player and Hyper-V are not compatible]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/vmware-player-and-hyper-v-are-not-compatible/"/>
        <updated>2015-04-12T11:28:34+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/vmware-player-and-hyper-v-are-not-compatible</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I run my VMs using vmware player for multiple operating system like Ubuntu, CentOS, Fedora, Suse,
Mint Linux. One fine day I noticed this error &ldquo;VMware Player and Hyper-V are not compatible&rdquo; from the vmplayer while
starting Ubuntu. This was bit surprising for me as I had run the same vm couple of times.</p>

<p>I realized that disabling the hyper-V could fix this problem, but I was still curious,
as of why could this start all of sudden?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The fix was simple as I said, to disable hyper-V</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='batch'><span class='line'>bcdedit <span class="n">/set</span> hypervisorlaunchtype <span class="k">off</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Rebooting the window&rsquo;s machine after running above command from command prompt with admin privilege fixes the problem.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jekyll Simply So Simple]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/jekyll-simply-so-simple/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-15T22:36:38+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/jekyll-simply-so-simple</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://rishijeet.github.io/images/jekyll.png" height="100" width="100" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>Jekyll one of the fast and simple static html page generator is really easy to start of with. I am so addicted to it now. Still exploring it more, there are so many features available and installing it
is as easy as it can be.</p>

<!-- more -->


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="o">~</span> <span class="err">$</span> <span class="n">gem</span> <span class="n">install</span> <span class="n">jekyll</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">~</span> <span class="err">$</span> <span class="n">jekyll</span> <span class="kp">new</span> <span class="n">my</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">awesome</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">site</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">~</span> <span class="err">$</span> <span class="n">cd</span> <span class="n">my</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">awesome</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">site</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">~</span><span class="sr">/my-awesome-site $ jekyll serve</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[PyCon India 2014]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/pycon-india-2014/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-15T21:57:01+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/pycon-india-2014</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://rishijeet.github.io/images/pycon.png" height="100" width="100" alt="Alt text" /> Yes, PyCon India 2014 is happening in Bangalore. <a href="http://in.pycon.org/2014/schedule.html#schedule_conference">Interesting topics</a> are on there for you on day 2.
Workshops are also been conducted as a part of day 1 program. I have attended the one in year 2012 and some of the topics were really good to know and worth attending.
The topics which focus on large data processing, performance, high scalable application in python, complex data structure would be worth to attend.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So as I see the topics on the PyCon India Website, if not changed, my favorite topic would be,<br/>
<a href="http://in.pycon.org/funnel/2014/108-python-spark-lightning-fast-cluster-computing">Python + Spark: Lightning Fast Cluster Computing</a><br/>
<a href="http://in.pycon.org/funnel/2014/227-django-design-patterns">Django Design Patterns</a><br/>
<a href="http://in.pycon.org/funnel/2014/150-new-scientific-plotting-in-python">New Scientific Plotting in Python</a><br/>
<a href="http://in.pycon.org/funnel/2014/165-faster-data-processing-in-python">Faster data processing in Python</a></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Convert from epoch to human readable date]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/convert-from-epoch-to-human-readable-date/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-12T23:50:56+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/convert-from-epoch-to-human-readable-date</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was stuck with an issue of converting the epoch time to human readable format, in my case
the epoch time was in milli sec, and I was getting all sort of <code>python ValueError: (22, 'Invalid argument')</code></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The fix was simple, to convert the epoch in milli sec to exact <code>date +%s</code> format
by slicing <code>[:3]</code></p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">time</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">time</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%a, </span><span class="si">%d</span><span class="s"> %b %Y %H:%M:%S +0000&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">time</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">localtime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">epoch</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">#Replace time.localtime with time.gmtime for GMT time.</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>



]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
