<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: scandals | Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/scandals/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-08-17T22:05:57+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electric Illusion: The Rise and Fall of BluSmart]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/electric-illusion-the-rise-and-fall-of-blusmart/"/>
        <updated>2025-06-15T20:38:26+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/electric-illusion-the-rise-and-fall-of-blusmart</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>BluSmart was once a symbol of India&rsquo;s clean energy aspirations — an all-electric ride-hailing platform backed by marquee investors and government lenders. With its zero-emissions fleet and no-surge pricing model, it quickly gained popularity in cities like Delhi and Bengaluru.</p>

<p>But behind the scenes, the startup’s success story unraveled into one of the most serious corporate fraud cases in India’s startup ecosystem. At the center of this financial maze was <strong>Gensol Engineering Ltd</strong>, a publicly listed company, controlled by the same promoters behind BluSmart. The ₹262 crore scandal that emerged in 2025 now implicates not just BluSmart, but Gensol’s board, finances, and investors.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/blusmart-logo.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<!--more-->


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-BluSmart-e2--80--99-s-Meteoric-Rise-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>BluSmart’s Meteoric Rise</strong></h3>

<p>Founded in 2019, BluSmart positioned itself as India’s first all-electric ride-hailing startup. The platform scaled rapidly:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Fleet</strong>: 8,000+ electric vehicles by 2024</li>
<li><strong>Coverage</strong>: Operational in Delhi-NCR, Mumbai, and Bengaluru</li>
<li><strong>Funding</strong>: ₹486+ crore in equity and ₹978 crore in loans from government-owned lenders</li>
<li><strong>Backers</strong>: BP Ventures, Mayfield Fund, and IREDA &amp; PFC via Gensol Engineering</li>
</ul>


<p>BluSmart&rsquo;s asset-light model hinged on one key arrangement — vehicle procurement and leasing handled by <strong>Gensol EV Lease Pvt Ltd</strong>, a subsidiary of <strong>Gensol Engineering Ltd</strong>, which was also promoted by the Jaggi brothers.</p>

<p>This relationship became the foundation of the scandal.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-How-Gensol-Became-the-Nexus-of-Fund-Diversion-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>How Gensol Became the Nexus of Fund Diversion</strong></h3>

<p>Gensol Engineering Ltd, listed on the Indian stock exchange, was the entity through which public sector lenders like <strong>IREDA</strong> (Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency) and <strong>PFC</strong> (Power Finance Corporation) disbursed nearly ₹978 crore in loans for electric vehicle procurement.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how the misuse played out:</p>

<a name="L1.--3c-strong-3e-Conflict-of-Interest-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>1. <strong>Conflict of Interest</strong></h4>

<p>Anmol and Puneet Jaggi held leadership roles in both <strong>BluSmart</strong> and <strong>Gensol</strong>. This dual control allowed them to shift funds and assets across entities without independent checks. While Gensol was meant to procure and lease EVs to BluSmart, the actual disbursement and usage of funds were poorly documented.</p>

<a name="L2.--3c-strong-3e-Falsified-Board-Resolutions-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>2. <strong>Falsified Board Resolutions</strong></h4>

<p>SEBI’s investigation revealed that board resolutions submitted to justify fund transfers from Gensol to other entities were <strong>forged</strong>. These resolutions claimed shareholder or board approvals that never took place.</p>

<a name="L3.--3c-strong-3e-Diversion-of-Funds-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>3. <strong>Diversion of Funds</strong></h4>

<p>Out of the ₹978 crore loan sanctioned to Gensol for 6,400 EVs:</p>

<ul>
<li>Only <strong>4,704 EVs</strong> were procured.</li>
<li>Over <strong>₹262 crore</strong> could not be accounted for.</li>
<li><p>Some funds were redirected to purchase <strong>personal assets</strong>, including:</p>

<ul>
<li>A ₹50 crore luxury apartment at DLF Camellias, Gurugram</li>
<li>Golf equipment worth ₹26 lakh</li>
<li>Foreign trips and personal company expenses</li>
<li>Transfers to family members and promoter-controlled entities</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<a name="L4.--3c-strong-3e-Blurring-the-Lines-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>4. <strong>Blurring the Lines</strong></h4>

<p>Because Gensol was the lender-facing entity and BluSmart was the consumer-facing app, the two were treated as distinct. However, in reality, the same core leadership ran both. This lack of separation allowed for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Overreporting of assets</li>
<li>Misleading investor communications</li>
<li>Obscuring of fund flows between listed and private companies</li>
</ul>


<a name="L5.--3c-strong-3e-Impact-on-Public-Markets-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>5. <strong>Impact on Public Markets</strong></h4>

<p>Gensol Engineering’s stock plummeted over 85% following SEBI&rsquo;s interim order. Investors who trusted the company’s renewable energy mission were blindsided by its role in enabling a startup’s financial misconduct.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Timeline-of-Events-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Timeline of Events</strong></h3>

<div class="timeline-container">
  <div class="timeline">
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">2019</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">BluSmart founded by Anmol and Puneet Jaggi</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">2021–2024</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">₹978 crore disbursed to Gensol for EV procurement</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">April 15, 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">SEBI interim order reveals ₹262 crore fund diversion via Gensol</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">April 17, 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">BluSmart halts operations across all cities</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">May 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">Grant Thornton appointed for forensic audit of Gensol and BluSmart</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">June 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">Delhi High Court orders seizure of over 700 EVs leased by Gensol to BluSmart</div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>




<style>
.timeline-container {
  max-width: 1000px;
  margin: 10px auto;
  padding: 20px;
  font-family: &#8216;Segoe UI&#8217;, sans-serif;
}

.timeline {
  display: flex;
  flex-wrap: wrap;
  justify-content: space-between;
  border-left: 4px solid #049CDB;
  padding-left: 20px;
  position: relative;
}

.timeline-event {
  position: relative;
  width: 100%;
  margin-bottom: 30px;
  padding-left: 20px;
}

.timeline-event::before {
  content: &#8221;;
  position: absolute;
  left: -12px;
  top: 8px;
  background-color: #049CDB;
  border: 3px solid white;
  border-radius: 50%;
  height: 16px;
  width: 16px;
  z-index: 1;
}

.timeline-date {
  font-weight: bold;
  font-size: 16px;
  color: #049CDB;
  margin-bottom: 5px;
}

.timeline-content {
  background: #f8f9fa;
  padding: 12px 16px;
  border-left: 4px solid #049CDB;
  border-radius: 6px;
  box-shadow: 0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,0.05);
}
</style>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Consequences-of-the-Scam-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Consequences of the Scam</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Investors and Markets</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Gensol’s credibility as a listed renewable energy company is under threat.</li>
<li>Public lenders like PFC and IREDA face scrutiny for failing to detect misuse earlier.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Regulatory Oversight</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SEBI’s action has prompted tighter surveillance of related-party transactions in startups.</li>
<li>The Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA) is reviewing whether more stringent cross-holding disclosures are required for startups using public debt.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Drivers and Users</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Over 10,000 drivers, mostly from underserved backgrounds, lost income overnight.</li>
<li>BluSmart customers are still awaiting wallet refunds or app updates.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Future of BluSmart</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Talks of reviving the company via an independent board or acquisition have emerged.</li>
<li>Some investors, including BP Ventures, may pursue legal action to recover their equity.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Lessons-from-Gensol-e2--80--93-BluSmart-Case-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Lessons from Gensol–BluSmart Case</strong></h3>

<div class="lessons-section">
  <div class="lessons-grid">
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Dual Leadership in Public/Private Firms</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Strong boundaries between promoter-led entities are essential.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Lack of Board Independence</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Board members should be empowered to question and audit all fund movements.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Weak Internal Controls</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Statutory audits must detect and flag multi-crore diversions early.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Misuse of Public Money</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Lending institutions need better tracking for disbursed capital.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>




<style>
.lessons-section {
  max-width: 1100px;
  margin: 10px auto;
  padding: 20px;
  font-family: &#8216;Segoe UI&#8217;, sans-serif;
}


.lessons-grid {
  display: grid;
  grid-template-columns: repeat(auto-fit, minmax(260px, 1fr));
  gap: 20px;
}

.lesson-card {
  border-left: 5px solid #049CDB;
  padding: 20px;
  border-radius: 8px;
  box-shadow: 0 2px 6px rgba(0,0,0,0.08);
  transition: transform 0.2s;
}

.lesson-card:hover {
  transform: translateY(-4px);
}

.issue-title {
  font-size: 18px;
  font-weight: bold;
  color: #049CDB;
  margin-bottom: 10px;
}

.lesson-text {
  font-size: 16px;
  color: #444;
  line-height: 1.5;
}
</style>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Conclusion-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>

<p>The BluSmart-Gensol scandal underscores a critical truth: governance is not optional. Innovation, sustainability, and market expansion are meaningless if built on opaque finances and related-party secrecy.</p>

<p>Gensol’s role in the BluSmart collapse shows how a listed company can be used as a conduit for private ambition if oversight is weak. As India’s startup ecosystem matures, this case should serve as a clear signal — accountability must scale along with vision.</p>

<p>BluSmart’s fall was not due to a lack of market demand or poor technology. It failed because of misaligned ethics, enabled by a public company that chose opacity over integrity.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[FTX Scandal 2023: Timeline, Facts, and Key Players]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/ftx-scandal-2023-timeline/"/>
        <updated>2025-06-14T13:49:37+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/ftx-scandal-2023-timeline</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the annals of modern financial history, few names have sparked as much controversy, disbelief, and chaos as <em>Futures Exchange (FTX)</em>. Once hailed as a shining star of the cryptocurrency world, FTX’s meteoric rise and catastrophic fall stunned investors, regulators, and the general public alike. By the end of 2023, the scandal surrounding FTX and its founder Sam Bankman-Fried had cemented its place as one of the largest and most complex financial frauds of the 21st century.</p>

<p>This blog dives into the rise and fall of FTX, examining the events that led to its collapse, the financial and human toll it took, and the key takeaways from a debacle that shook the entire crypto industry to its core.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/ftx.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Rise-of-FTX:-From-Start-2d-up-to-Crypto-Juggernaut"></a>
<h3>The Rise of FTX: From Start-up to Crypto Juggernaut</h3>

<p>FTX was founded in 2019 by Sam Bankman-Fried (commonly referred to as SBF), a former Wall Street quant with a background from MIT and a reputation for genius-level intellect. The exchange was created as a more sophisticated platform for cryptocurrency derivatives and quickly attracted traders looking for advanced features, high leverage, and innovative products.</p>

<p>By 2021, FTX had:</p>

<ul>
<li>Raised over <strong>\$1.8 billion</strong> from prominent investors including Sequoia Capital, SoftBank, and Tiger Global.</li>
<li>Claimed <strong>over 1 million users</strong> and processed billions of dollars in trades daily.</li>
<li>Achieved a staggering <strong>\$32 billion valuation</strong>, making it the <strong>third-largest crypto exchange</strong> globally.</li>
</ul>


<p>SBF’s influence extended well beyond the company. He was a frequent guest on financial talk shows, lobbied in Washington, and was dubbed the “JP Morgan of crypto” after bailing out other struggling crypto firms in 2022. But behind the charismatic image and philanthropic posturing was a house of cards waiting to collapse.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="/images/2025/ftx_revenue.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Fall-Begins:-A-Leak-2c--a-Tweet-2c--and-a-Run-on-the-Bank"></a>
<h3>The Fall Begins: A Leak, a Tweet, and a Run on the Bank</h3>

<p>The trigger came in <strong>early November 2022</strong>, when <em>CoinDesk</em> published a leaked balance sheet from Alameda Research, a trading firm closely tied to FTX and also founded by SBF. The leak revealed that:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>\$5.8 billion</strong> of Alameda’s assets were in <strong>FTT</strong>, the native token issued by FTX.</li>
<li>A large portion of Alameda&rsquo;s balance sheet was illiquid and backed by FTT, suggesting FTX and Alameda were dangerously intertwined.</li>
</ul>


<p>This revelation sparked panic in the market. <strong>Binance</strong>, FTX’s main rival, announced it would liquidate its <strong>\$530 million</strong> worth of FTT holdings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/FTX_token_price.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<p>What followed was a textbook “run on the bank.” Within <strong>72 hours</strong>, FTX customers tried to withdraw <strong>\$6 billion</strong>, exposing the exchange’s inability to meet withdrawal demands. On <strong>November 11, 2022</strong>, FTX, Alameda Research, and over 130 related entities filed for bankruptcy.</p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Aftermath:-Bankruptcy-2c--Arrests-2c--and-a-Trial"></a>
<h3>The Aftermath: Bankruptcy, Arrests, and a Trial</h3>

<p>The bankruptcy filings laid bare the chaos within FTX:</p>

<ul>
<li>An estimated <strong>\$8–10 billion</strong> in customer funds were <strong>missing</strong>.</li>
<li>FTX had <strong>no proper financial records</strong>, and assets were reportedly tracked in <strong>QuickBooks</strong>, a tool meant for small businesses.</li>
<li>The new CEO, <strong>John J. Ray III</strong> (who previously oversaw Enron’s liquidation), called FTX&rsquo;s management the worst he’d seen in his 40-year career.</li>
</ul>


<p>In <strong>December 2022</strong>, SBF was arrested in the Bahamas and extradited to the U.S. He was charged with <strong>eight counts</strong> of fraud, money laundering, and campaign finance violations.</p>

<p>During the 2023 trial:</p>

<ul>
<li>Testimonies from former FTX executives (including Caroline Ellison, CEO of Alameda and SBF’s former girlfriend) revealed deliberate misappropriation of customer funds.</li>
<li>Prosecutors showed that billions were siphoned from FTX to fund Alameda’s risky bets, luxury real estate, political donations (over <strong>\$90 million</strong>), and personal expenses.</li>
</ul>


<p>In <strong>November 2023</strong>, Sam Bankman-Fried was found <strong>guilty on all counts</strong>, facing a potential sentence of over <strong>110 years</strong> in prison. His sentencing is scheduled for <strong>March 2024</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Numbers-That-Define-the-Collapse"></a>
<h3>The Numbers That Define the Collapse</h3>

<style>
  .ftx-table {
    width: 100%;
    border-collapse: collapse;
    margin: 20px 0;
    font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 16px;
  }

  .ftx-table th, .ftx-table td {
    border: 1px solid #ddd;
    padding: 12px 16px;
    text-align: left;
  }

  .ftx-table th {
    background-color: #f4f4f4;
    font-weight: bold;
  }

  .ftx-table tr:nth-child(even) {
    background-color: #f9f9f9;
  }

  .ftx-table tr:hover {
    background-color: #f1f1f1;
  }
</style>




<table class="ftx-table">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Metric</th>
      <th>Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Peak Valuation of FTX</td>
      <td>$32 billion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Customer Funds Missing</td>
      <td>~$8–10 billion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Number of Users Affected</td>
      <td>Over 1 million</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Political Donations by SBF</td>
      <td>$90 million+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Real Estate Purchases</td>
      <td>$300 million+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Alameda Loan to SBF</td>
      <td>$1 billion+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Legal and Bankruptcy Costs</td>
      <td>Estimated $200 million+</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>


<hr />

<a name="Broader-Impact-on-Crypto-and-Beyond"></a>
<h3>Broader Impact on Crypto and Beyond</h3>

<p>FTX’s collapse sent shockwaves through the crypto ecosystem:</p>

<ul>
<li>Prices of major cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum dropped over <strong>20%</strong> in the weeks following the collapse.</li>
<li>Several crypto lending platforms and hedge funds with FTX exposure, including <strong>Genesis</strong> and <strong>BlockFi</strong>, filed for bankruptcy.</li>
<li>Investors lost trust in centralized exchanges, pushing many toward <strong>cold wallets</strong> and <strong>DeFi platforms</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Regulators responded swiftly:</p>

<ul>
<li>U.S. Congress held hearings on crypto regulation.</li>
<li>The SEC and CFTC vowed tighter oversight of crypto platforms.</li>
<li>Discussions began around creating a federal framework for <strong>crypto custodianship</strong> and <strong>proof-of-reserves</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Lessons-from-the-FTX-Scandal"></a>
<h3>Lessons from the FTX Scandal</h3>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Charisma is not competence</strong>
SBF’s charm, intelligence, and philanthropic front masked serious mismanagement and fraudulent practices.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Regulatory gaps need closing</strong>
FTX operated in a regulatory gray zone, exploiting jurisdictional loopholes to avoid scrutiny.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Centralization without accountability is dangerous</strong>
Despite being a crypto exchange, FTX was run like a black box. There were no independent board members or external audits.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Always follow the money</strong>
The FTX saga revealed the ease with which customer funds could be co-mingled and misused in the absence of checks and balances.</p></li>
</ol>


<hr />

<a name="Final-Thoughts"></a>
<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>FTX was not just a crypto story—it was a human story of unchecked power, blind trust, and systemic failure. It shook investor confidence and became a harsh reminder that, even in the futuristic world of blockchain, age-old rules of governance, transparency, and ethics cannot be ignored.</p>

<p>As the crypto industry tries to rebuild in the wake of this collapse, FTX will stand as a cautionary tale—a reminder that even billion-dollar empires can crumble when built on deception.</p>

<p>Let this not just be history, but a lesson for the future.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
