<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: fmcg | Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/fmcg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-03-09T21:16:48+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coca-Cola: A Legacy of Success, Controversy, and Resilience]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/coca-cola-a-legacy-of-success/"/>
        <updated>2025-03-09T21:07:15+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/coca-cola-a-legacy-of-success</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Coca-Cola is one of the most iconic brands in the world, with a history spanning over a century. It has become synonymous with soft drinks, creating a massive global presence. This case study explores Coca-Cola’s success story, key crises, and scandals, as well as how the company has managed to remain a market leader for so long.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/coca_cola.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="The-Success-Story"></a>
<h2>The Success Story</h2>

<a name="Origins-and-Early-Growth"></a>
<h3>Origins and Early Growth</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola was invented in 1886 by Dr. John Stith Pemberton in Atlanta, Georgia.</li>
<li>The formula was later bought by Asa Candler, who aggressively marketed it and expanded distribution.</li>
<li>By 1895, Coca-Cola was sold across the United States.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Market-Domination"></a>
<h3>Market Domination</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola became a household name through <strong>branding, advertising, and distribution</strong>.</li>
<li>By 1919, the company was sold to a group of investors for <strong>$25 million</strong>.</li>
<li>The introduction of the iconic <strong>contour bottle in 1915</strong> helped distinguish Coca-Cola from competitors.</li>
<li>The company’s famous Santa Claus campaign in the 1930s reinforced its association with happiness and celebration.</li>
<li>By the 1950s, Coca-Cola had expanded into more than <strong>100 countries</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<a name="Product-Diversification"></a>
<h3>Product Diversification</h3>

<ul>
<li>In response to changing consumer preferences, Coca-Cola introduced products such as <strong>Diet Coke (1982), Coca-Cola Zero (2005), and Coca-Cola Life (2013)</strong>.</li>
<li>The company expanded into other beverage categories, acquiring <strong>Minute Maid (1960), Dasani (1999), and Costa Coffee (2018)</strong>.</li>
<li>Today, Coca-Cola owns over <strong>500 brands</strong> across more than <strong>200 countries</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Financial-Strength"></a>
<h3>Financial Strength</h3>

<ul>
<li>As of 2023, Coca-Cola’s annual revenue was <strong>$43 billion</strong>.</li>
<li>It holds a global market share of <strong>nearly 50%</strong> in the carbonated soft drinks industry.</li>
<li>The company spends <strong>over $4 billion annually</strong> on marketing and advertising.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Key-Facts--26-amp-3b--Figures"></a>
<h3>Key Facts &amp; Figures</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Founded:</strong> 1886</li>
<li><strong>Annual Revenue (2023):</strong> $43 billion</li>
<li><strong>Number of Countries Operated In:</strong> 200+</li>
<li><strong>Brands Owned:</strong> 500+</li>
<li><strong>Global Market Share (Soft Drinks):</strong> ~50%</li>
<li><strong>Annual Advertising Spend:</strong> $4 billion+</li>
<li><strong>Employees:</strong> 79,000+</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Major-Crises-and-Scandals"></a>
<h2>Major Crises and Scandals</h2>

<a name="The--22-New-Coke-22--Disaster--28-1985-29-"></a>
<h3>The &ldquo;New Coke&rdquo; Disaster (1985)</h3>

<ul>
<li>In 1985, Coca-Cola reformulated its flagship product, replacing it with &ldquo;New Coke.&rdquo;</li>
<li>The change sparked widespread backlash, with over <strong>400,000 complaints</strong> from customers.</li>
<li>Coca-Cola reintroduced the original formula as &ldquo;Coca-Cola Classic&rdquo; within <strong>79 days</strong>, turning the fiasco into a marketing triumph.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/new_coke.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Racial-Discrimination-Lawsuit--28-1999-29-"></a>
<h3>Racial Discrimination Lawsuit (1999)</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola faced a <strong>$192.5 million settlement</strong> after being sued for racial discrimination in hiring and promotions.</li>
<li>The lawsuit led to significant changes in the company’s diversity and inclusion policies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="India-Pesticide-Controversy--28-2003-2d-2006-29-"></a>
<h3>India Pesticide Controversy (2003-2006)</h3>

<ul>
<li>A study in India found that Coca-Cola products contained pesticide residues <strong>24 times above European standards</strong>.</li>
<li>Sales dropped significantly in India, leading to factory closures and government scrutiny.</li>
<li>Coca-Cola later invested in <strong>water conservation projects</strong> and sustainability efforts to repair its image.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Water-Usage--26-amp-3b--Environmental-Concerns"></a>
<h3>Water Usage &amp; Environmental Concerns</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola has faced criticism over excessive water usage, particularly in water-scarce regions.</li>
<li>In 2007, it pledged to become <strong>water neutral by 2020</strong>, a goal it claims to have met by replenishing <strong>100% of the water used</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Coca-2d-Cola-and-Health-Concerns"></a>
<h3>Coca-Cola and Health Concerns</h3>

<ul>
<li>The company has been accused of contributing to the global obesity crisis.</li>
<li>In 2015, reports emerged that Coca-Cola funded research downplaying the role of sugary drinks in obesity.</li>
<li>In response, Coca-Cola introduced <strong>low-sugar and no-sugar options</strong> and expanded its portfolio to include healthier beverages.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Strategies-for-Long-2d-Term-Success"></a>
<h2>Strategies for Long-Term Success</h2>

<a name="Strong-Branding--26-amp-3b--Marketing"></a>
<h3>Strong Branding &amp; Marketing</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola’s brand is valued at <strong>over $89 billion</strong>, making it one of the most recognized in the world.</li>
<li>The &ldquo;Share a Coke&rdquo; campaign (2011) personalized bottles, driving a <strong>2% increase in sales</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Global-Expansion--26-amp-3b--Localization"></a>
<h3>Global Expansion &amp; Localization</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola adapts its products to regional tastes. In Japan, for instance, it sells <strong>green tea and coffee variants</strong>.</li>
<li>It has established a vast distribution network, ensuring availability in <strong>even the most remote areas</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Innovation--26-amp-3b--Product-Adaptation"></a>
<h3>Innovation &amp; Product Adaptation</h3>

<ul>
<li>The company has continuously introduced new beverages, including <strong>plant-based and functional drinks</strong>.</li>
<li>Investments in sustainability and health-focused products help maintain relevance in changing markets.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/coke_brands.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Crisis-Management--26-amp-3b--Adaptability"></a>
<h3>Crisis Management &amp; Adaptability</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola’s ability to pivot quickly, such as during the &ldquo;New Coke&rdquo; crisis, has been key to maintaining customer trust.</li>
<li>Transparency and corporate social responsibility efforts have helped it recover from controversies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Coca-Cola’s longevity can be attributed to <strong>strong branding, global expansion, adaptability, and crisis management</strong>. Despite facing significant challenges, the company remains a market leader due to its ability to evolve and stay relevant in a changing world.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Lipton – A Global Tea Powerhouse]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-lipton-a-global-tea-powerhouse/"/>
        <updated>2025-02-26T18:16:23+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-lipton-a-global-tea-powerhouse</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the bustling streets of Glasgow, Scotland, in the 1870s, a young, ambitious entrepreneur named Sir Thomas Lipton had a vision—to make tea, once a luxury for the elite, accessible to everyone. Little did he know that his dream would evolve into a global tea empire that would redefine the industry for generations to come.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/lipton_logo.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-The-Humble-Beginnings-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>The Humble Beginnings</strong></h2>

<p>Thomas Lipton, born in 1848 to Irish immigrant parents, was no stranger to hard work. At the age of 15, he sailed to the United States, where he took up various jobs, including working in a grocery store. Observing the efficiency of American retail operations, he returned to Scotland with a dream of revolutionizing the food trade.</p>

<p>In 1871, at the age of 23, Lipton opened his first grocery store in Glasgow. He marketed his store as offering “the best goods at the cheapest prices,” a philosophy that won the hearts of working-class families. His business grew rapidly, and by the 1880s, he owned over 300 stores across Britain. But Lipton was always thinking bigger.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="/images/2025/lipton.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Breaking-Into-the-Tea-Industry-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Breaking Into the Tea Industry</strong></h2>

<p>During the late 19th century, tea was an expensive luxury, controlled by middlemen who inflated prices. Lipton saw an opportunity. Rather than relying on suppliers, he decided to cut out the middlemen and source tea directly from plantations in Ceylon (modern-day Sri Lanka). He bought vast tea estates, ensuring quality control and reducing costs.</p>

<p>To market his tea, Lipton leveraged his exceptional promotional skills. He sponsored hot air balloon events, used colorful advertisements, and even hired elephants to parade through London’s streets carrying Lipton Tea chests. His genius lay in making tea not just affordable but desirable.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Tea-for-the-Masses-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Tea for the Masses</strong></h2>

<p>Lipton introduced the concept of pre-packaged tea, a revolutionary idea at the time. Until then, tea was sold loose, and quality varied. By branding and packaging his tea, he guaranteed consistency, making it more appealing to customers. His slogan, “Direct from the Tea Gardens to the Teapot,” became synonymous with freshness and affordability.</p>

<p>By 1890, Lipton Tea was a household name in Britain, and soon, it spread across Europe and America. He even earned a royal warrant as the official tea supplier to Queen Victoria—a remarkable feat for a man who started with a single grocery store.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Global-Expansion-and-Innovations-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Global Expansion and Innovations</strong></h2>

<p>In the early 20th century, Lipton continued expanding, setting up distribution channels worldwide. One of the most significant milestones came in the 1950s when Lipton became part of the Unilever conglomerate, giving it access to unparalleled resources and global reach.</p>

<p>As consumer habits evolved, Lipton adapted. The introduction of tea bags in the 1950s and ready-to-drink iced tea in the 1990s revolutionized the industry. Lipton embraced health-conscious trends, launching green teas, herbal infusions, and organic blends.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Fun-Facts-and-Data-Points-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Fun Facts and Data Points</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Lipton Today</strong>: Sold in over <strong>110 countries</strong>, Lipton is one of the world’s most recognizable tea brands.</li>
<li><strong>Tea Production</strong>: Lipton sources tea from <strong>more than 600 tea estates</strong> worldwide.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental Commitment</strong>: Lipton has committed to <strong>100% Rainforest Alliance Certified tea</strong>, ensuring sustainable farming practices.</li>
<li><strong>Marketing Genius</strong>: In 1929, Lipton launched one of the first-ever radio commercials in America, setting the stage for modern advertising strategies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-The-Legacy-of-Lipton-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>The Legacy of Lipton</strong></h2>

<p>From a single grocery store in Glasgow to a global powerhouse, Lipton’s journey is a testament to innovation, persistence, and an unyielding belief in making quality tea accessible to all. Sir Thomas Lipton’s legacy endures not just in every cup of Lipton tea enjoyed worldwide but in the very fabric of modern retail and branding strategies.</p>

<p>So, the next time you sip on a warm cup of Lipton tea, remember—you’re not just drinking tea; you’re tasting a rich history steeped in vision and ingenuity.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
