<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: event | Rishijeet Mishra | Technologist | Tech Trends & Development Blog]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/event/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-10-11T16:55:39+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vert.x: The Reactive Toolkit for Modern Applications]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/vert-dot-x-the-reactive-toolkit-for-modern-applications/"/>
        <updated>2024-08-03T23:22:56+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/vert-dot-x-the-reactive-toolkit-for-modern-applications</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the realm of modern web applications, responsiveness and scalability are paramount. Vert.x, a toolkit for building reactive applications on the JVM, stands out due to its performance and flexibility. Vert.x is polyglot, allowing developers to use multiple languages such as Java, JavaScript, Groovy, Ruby, Kotlin, and Scala. Its non-blocking nature and event-driven architecture make it an excellent choice for developing high-throughput, low-latency applications.</p>

<p>In this blog, we&rsquo;ll explore the unique aspects of Vert.x, how it leverages the reactive programming model, and provide examples to illustrate its capabilities.
<img src="/images/2024/vertx.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="What-Makes-Vert.x-Unique-3f-"></a>
<h2>What Makes Vert.x Unique?</h2>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Polyglot-Support-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Polyglot Support</strong></h3>

<p>Vert.x allows developers to write applications in multiple languages, providing flexibility and enabling teams to use the best language for their needs.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Event-2d-Driven-and-Non-2d-Blocking-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Event-Driven and Non-Blocking</strong></h3>

<p>Vert.x uses a non-blocking, event-driven model, allowing it to handle many concurrent connections with minimal threads. This leads to better resource utilization and scalability.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Reactive-Programming-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Reactive Programming</strong></h3>

<p>Vert.x embraces reactive programming principles, making it easier to build responsive, resilient, and elastic applications. It integrates seamlessly with reactive libraries like RxJava and Reactor.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Verticles-and-Event-Bus-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Verticles and Event Bus</strong></h3>

<p>Vert.x applications are composed of Verticles, which are units of deployment and concurrency. The Event Bus facilitates communication between Verticles, enabling a highly decoupled architecture.</p>

<!--more-->


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Module-System-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Module System</strong></h3>

<p>Vert.x offers a powerful module system, allowing for easy reuse and deployment of components.</p>

<a name="Getting-Started-with-Vert.x"></a>
<h2>Getting Started with Vert.x</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s walk through setting up a simple Vert.x application and explore its features.</p>

<a name="Example:-Setting-Up-a-Vert.x-Project"></a>
<h3>Example: Setting Up a Vert.x Project</h3>

<a name="Project-Structure"></a>
<h4>Project Structure</h4>

<p>We&rsquo;ll create a basic Vert.x application in Java. Ensure you have Maven or Gradle installed.</p>

<a name="Maven-Project-Setup"></a>
<h4>Maven Project Setup</h4>

<p><strong>pom.xml:</strong></p>

<pre><code class="xml">&lt;project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/maven-4.0.0.xsd"&gt;
    &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;

    &lt;groupId&gt;com.example&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;vertx-demo&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;1.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;

    &lt;properties&gt;
        &lt;maven.compiler.source&gt;11&lt;/maven.compiler.source&gt;
        &lt;maven.compiler.target&gt;11&lt;/maven.compiler.target&gt;
        &lt;vertx.version&gt;4.3.4&lt;/vertx.version&gt;
    &lt;/properties&gt;

    &lt;dependencies&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;io.vertx&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;vertx-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;${vertx.version}&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;io.vertx&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;vertx-web&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;${vertx.version}&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;/dependencies&gt;

    &lt;build&gt;
        &lt;plugins&gt;
            &lt;plugin&gt;
                &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
                &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-compiler-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                &lt;version&gt;3.8.1&lt;/version&gt;
            &lt;/plugin&gt;
            &lt;plugin&gt;
                &lt;groupId&gt;io.fabric8&lt;/groupId&gt;
                &lt;artifactId&gt;docker-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                &lt;version&gt;0.34.1&lt;/version&gt;
            &lt;/plugin&gt;
        &lt;/plugins&gt;
    &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</code></pre>

<a name="Example:-Creating-a-Simple-HTTP-Server"></a>
<h3>Example: Creating a Simple HTTP Server</h3>

<a name="Main-Verticle"></a>
<h4>Main Verticle</h4>

<pre><code class="java">package com.example;

import io.vertx.core.AbstractVerticle;
import io.vertx.core.Vertx;
import io.vertx.ext.web.Router;
import io.vertx.ext.web.RoutingContext;

public class MainVerticle extends AbstractVerticle {

    @Override
    public void start() {
        Router router = Router.router(vertx);
        router.route("/").handler(this::handleRoot);

        vertx.createHttpServer()
             .requestHandler(router)
             .listen(8888, result -&gt; {
                 if (result.succeeded()) {
                     System.out.println("Server started on port 8888");
                 } else {
                     System.out.println("Failed to start server: " + result.cause());
                 }
             });
    }

    private void handleRoot(RoutingContext context) {
        context.response()
               .putHeader("content-type", "text/plain")
               .end("Hello, Rishijeet!");
    }

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Vertx vertx = Vertx.vertx();
        vertx.deployVerticle(new MainVerticle());
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This simple Vert.x application sets up an HTTP server that listens on port 8888 and responds with &ldquo;Hello, Rishijeet!&rdquo;
when the root URL is accessed.</p>

<a name="Example:-Deploying-Verticles"></a>
<h3>Example: Deploying Verticles</h3>

<p>Vert.x applications are composed of Verticles. You can deploy multiple Verticles, enabling a modular and scalable architecture.</p>

<a name="Worker-Verticle"></a>
<h4>Worker Verticle</h4>

<pre><code class="java">package com.example;

import io.vertx.core.AbstractVerticle;
import io.vertx.core.Promise;

public class WorkerVerticle extends AbstractVerticle {

    @Override
    public void start(Promise&lt;Void&gt; startPromise) {
        vertx.setPeriodic(1000, id -&gt; {
            System.out.println("Worker Verticle: " + Thread.currentThread().getName());
        });
        startPromise.complete();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<a name="Deploying-Verticles"></a>
<h4>Deploying Verticles</h4>

<pre><code class="java">package com.example;

import io.vertx.core.Vertx;

public class MainApp {
    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Vertx vertx = Vertx.vertx();
        vertx.deployVerticle(new MainVerticle());
        vertx.deployVerticle(new WorkerVerticle());
    }
}
</code></pre>

<a name="Example:-Using-the-Event-Bus"></a>
<h3>Example: Using the Event Bus</h3>

<p>The Event Bus allows Verticles to communicate asynchronously.</p>

<a name="Sender-Verticle"></a>
<h4>Sender Verticle</h4>

<pre><code class="java">package com.example;

import io.vertx.core.AbstractVerticle;
import io.vertx.core.Vertx;

public class SenderVerticle extends AbstractVerticle {

    @Override
    public void start() {
        vertx.eventBus().send("example.address", "Hello from SenderVerticle!");
    }

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Vertx vertx = Vertx.vertx();
        vertx.deployVerticle(new SenderVerticle());
    }
}
</code></pre>

<a name="Receiver-Verticle"></a>
<h4>Receiver Verticle</h4>

<pre><code class="java">package com.example;

import io.vertx.core.AbstractVerticle;
import io.vertx.core.Vertx;

public class ReceiverVerticle extends AbstractVerticle {

    @Override
    public void start() {
        vertx.eventBus().consumer("example.address", message -&gt; {
            System.out.println("Received message: " + message.body());
        });
    }

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        Vertx vertx = Vertx.vertx();
        vertx.deployVerticle(new ReceiverVerticle());
    }
}
</code></pre>

<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Vert.x offers a powerful and flexible toolkit for building modern, reactive applications. Its unique features, including polyglot support, non-blocking event-driven architecture, and the Event Bus, make it an excellent choice for high-throughput, low-latency applications. By leveraging Verticles and the reactive programming model, developers can build scalable, maintainable, and efficient applications.</p>

<p>Understanding the power of Vert.x and how to use its features effectively can significantly improve the responsiveness and scalability of your applications. Whether you&rsquo;re building microservices, real-time web applications, or IoT solutions, Vert.x provides the tools you need to succeed.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Event-Driven Architecture: Unlocking Modern Application Potential]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/event-driven-architecture-unlocking-modern-application-potential/"/>
        <updated>2024-06-26T09:27:40+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/event-driven-architecture-unlocking-modern-application-potential</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In today&rsquo;s fast-paced digital landscape, real-time data processing and responsive systems are becoming increasingly crucial. Traditional request-response architectures often struggle to keep up with the demands of modern applications, which require scalable, resilient, and decoupled systems. Enter event-based architecture—a paradigm that addresses these challenges by enabling systems to react to changes and events as they happen.</p>

<p>In this blog, we&rsquo;ll explore the key concepts, benefits, and components of modern event-based architecture, along with practical examples and best practices for implementation.</p>

<a name="What-is-Event-2d-Based-Architecture-3f-"></a>
<h2>What is Event-Based Architecture?</h2>

<p>Event-based architecture is a design pattern in which system components communicate by producing and consuming events. An event is a significant change in state or an occurrence that is meaningful to the system, such as a user action, a data update, or an external trigger. Instead of directly calling methods or services, components publish events to an event bus, and other components subscribe to these events to perform actions in response.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/glossary-eda.svg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Hazelcast</em></p>

<a name="Components-of-Modern-Event-2d-Based-Architecture"></a>
<h2>Components of Modern Event-Based Architecture</h2>

<a name="Event-Producers"></a>
<h3>Event Producers</h3>

<p>Event producers are responsible for generating events. These can be user interfaces, IoT devices, data ingestion services, or any other source that generates meaningful events. Producers publish events to the event bus without needing to know who will consume them.</p>

<a name="Event-Consumers"></a>
<h3>Event Consumers</h3>

<p>Event consumers subscribe to specific events and react to them. Consumers can perform various actions, such as updating databases, triggering workflows, sending notifications, or invoking other services. Each consumer processes events independently, allowing for parallel and asynchronous processing.</p>

<a name="Event-Bus"></a>
<h3>Event Bus</h3>

<p>The event bus is the backbone of an event-based architecture. It routes events from producers to consumers, ensuring reliable and scalable communication. Common implementations of an event bus include message brokers like Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ, and Amazon SNS/SQS.</p>

<a name="Event-Streams-and-Storage"></a>
<h3>Event Streams and Storage</h3>

<p>Event streams are continuous flows of events that can be processed in real-time or stored for batch processing and historical analysis. Stream processing frameworks like Apache Kafka Streams, Apache Flink, and Apache Storm enable real-time processing of event streams.</p>

<a name="Event-Processing-and-Transformation"></a>
<h3>Event Processing and Transformation</h3>

<p>Event processing involves filtering, aggregating, and transforming events to derive meaningful insights and trigger actions. Complex Event Processing (CEP) engines and stream processing frameworks are often used to handle sophisticated event processing requirements.</p>

<!--more-->


<a name="Practical-Example"></a>
<h2>Practical Example</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s map the modern event-based architecture to a coffee shop scenario with four key services: Product Service, Counter Service, Barista Service, and Kitchen Service. This analogy will help visualize how event-based systems work in a real-world context.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2024/coffeeshop.svg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: <a href="https://github.com/thangchung/go-coffeeshop">Github</a></em></p>

<a name="Services-in-the-Coffee-Shop"></a>
<h3>Services in the Coffee Shop</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Product Service</strong>: Manages the menu and availability of items.</li>
<li><strong>Counter Service</strong>: Handles customer orders and payments.</li>
<li><strong>Barista Service</strong>: Prepares coffee and other beverages.</li>
<li><strong>Kitchen Service</strong>: Prepares food items like pastries and sandwiches.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Event-Flow-in-the-Coffee-Shop"></a>
<h3>Event Flow in the Coffee Shop</h3>

<a name="Customer-Places-an-Order"></a>
<h4>Customer Places an Order</h4>

<ul>
<li><strong>Order Received</strong>: A customer places an order at the counter. The Counter Service generates an &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; event
containing details of the order.</li>
<li><strong>Inventory Check</strong>: The Product Service subscribes to &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; events to verify the availability of items. If
an item is out of stock, it can trigger an &ldquo;ItemOutOfStock&rdquo; event to update the menu.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Order-Processing"></a>
<h4>Order Processing</h4>

<ul>
<li><strong>Beverage Preparation</strong>: The Barista Service subscribes to &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; events to start preparing beverages. Once
a beverage is ready, it generates an &ldquo;BeverageReady&rdquo; event.</li>
<li><strong>Food Preparation</strong>: The Kitchen Service subscribes to &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; events to start preparing food items. Once a
food item is ready, it generates an &ldquo;FoodReady&rdquo; event.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Customer-Notification"></a>
<h4>Customer Notification</h4>

<ul>
<li><strong>Order Ready Notification</strong>: The Counter Service subscribes to &ldquo;BeverageReady&rdquo; and &ldquo;FoodReady&rdquo; events. When all
items in an order are ready, it generates an &ldquo;OrderReady&rdquo; event and notifies the customer.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Detailed-Event-Flow"></a>
<h3>Detailed Event Flow</h3>

<p><strong>Order Placed</strong>:
    - A customer orders a cappuccino and a sandwich at the counter.
    - The Counter Service generates an &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; event:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "orderId": "12345",
    "items": [
        {"type": "beverage", "name": "cappuccino"},
        {"type": "food", "name": "sandwich"}
    ]
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Inventory Check</strong>:
    - The Product Service receives the &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; event and checks inventory.
    - If the cappuccino is out of stock, it generates an &ldquo;ItemOutOfStock&rdquo; event.
    - If all items are available, no further action is taken by the Product Service.</p>

<p><strong>Beverage Preparation</strong>:
    - The Barista Service receives the &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; event and starts preparing the cappuccino.
    - Once the cappuccino is ready, it generates a &ldquo;BeverageReady&rdquo; event:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "orderId": "12345",
    "item": "cappuccino"
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Food Preparation</strong>:
    - The Kitchen Service receives the &ldquo;OrderPlaced&rdquo; event and starts preparing the sandwich.
    - Once the sandwich is ready, it generates a &ldquo;FoodReady&rdquo; event:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "orderId": "12345",
    "item": "sandwich"
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Order Ready Notification</strong>:
    - The Counter Service receives both &ldquo;BeverageReady&rdquo; and &ldquo;FoodReady&rdquo; events.
    - Once all items for order 12345 are ready, it generates an &ldquo;OrderReady&rdquo; event and notifies the customer:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "orderId": "12345",
    "status": "ready"
}
</code></pre>

<a name="Best-Practices-for-Implementing-Event-2d-Based-Architecture"></a>
<h2>Best Practices for Implementing Event-Based Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Design for Idempotency</strong>: Ensure that event consumers can handle duplicate events gracefully, as network issues
might cause events to be delivered multiple times.</li>
<li><strong>Use Schemas</strong>: Define clear schemas for events to ensure consistent and reliable communication between producers
and consumers.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor and Log</strong>: Implement robust monitoring and logging to track event flows, detect anomalies, and
troubleshoot issues.</li>
<li><strong>Handle Event Ordering</strong>: If event order is important, ensure that your event bus or stream processing framework
preserves the order of events.</li>
<li><strong>Ensure Fault Tolerance</strong>: Design your system to handle failures gracefully, with retry mechanisms and fallback
strategies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Modern event-based architecture provides a robust and flexible approach to building scalable, resilient, and real-time systems. By decoupling components and enabling asynchronous communication through events, this architecture pattern addresses many challenges of traditional systems. Whether you&rsquo;re building an e-commerce platform, a real-time analytics system, or an IoT solution, event-based architecture can help you achieve better performance, scalability, and agility.</p>

<p>Embracing this architectural style requires careful planning, but the benefits it offers make it a worthwhile investment for any modern application.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
