<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: case_study | Rishijeet Mishra | Technologist | Tech Trends & Development Blog]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/case-study/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-09-08T09:53:15+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electric Illusion: The Rise and Fall of BluSmart]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/electric-illusion-the-rise-and-fall-of-blusmart/"/>
        <updated>2025-06-15T20:38:26+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/electric-illusion-the-rise-and-fall-of-blusmart</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>BluSmart was once a symbol of India&rsquo;s clean energy aspirations — an all-electric ride-hailing platform backed by marquee investors and government lenders. With its zero-emissions fleet and no-surge pricing model, it quickly gained popularity in cities like Delhi and Bengaluru.</p>

<p>But behind the scenes, the startup’s success story unraveled into one of the most serious corporate fraud cases in India’s startup ecosystem. At the center of this financial maze was <strong>Gensol Engineering Ltd</strong>, a publicly listed company, controlled by the same promoters behind BluSmart. The ₹262 crore scandal that emerged in 2025 now implicates not just BluSmart, but Gensol’s board, finances, and investors.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/blusmart-logo.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<!--more-->


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-BluSmart-e2--80--99-s-Meteoric-Rise-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>BluSmart’s Meteoric Rise</strong></h3>

<p>Founded in 2019, BluSmart positioned itself as India’s first all-electric ride-hailing startup. The platform scaled rapidly:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Fleet</strong>: 8,000+ electric vehicles by 2024</li>
<li><strong>Coverage</strong>: Operational in Delhi-NCR, Mumbai, and Bengaluru</li>
<li><strong>Funding</strong>: ₹486+ crore in equity and ₹978 crore in loans from government-owned lenders</li>
<li><strong>Backers</strong>: BP Ventures, Mayfield Fund, and IREDA &amp; PFC via Gensol Engineering</li>
</ul>


<p>BluSmart&rsquo;s asset-light model hinged on one key arrangement — vehicle procurement and leasing handled by <strong>Gensol EV Lease Pvt Ltd</strong>, a subsidiary of <strong>Gensol Engineering Ltd</strong>, which was also promoted by the Jaggi brothers.</p>

<p>This relationship became the foundation of the scandal.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-How-Gensol-Became-the-Nexus-of-Fund-Diversion-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>How Gensol Became the Nexus of Fund Diversion</strong></h3>

<p>Gensol Engineering Ltd, listed on the Indian stock exchange, was the entity through which public sector lenders like <strong>IREDA</strong> (Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency) and <strong>PFC</strong> (Power Finance Corporation) disbursed nearly ₹978 crore in loans for electric vehicle procurement.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how the misuse played out:</p>

<a name="L1.--3c-strong-3e-Conflict-of-Interest-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>1. <strong>Conflict of Interest</strong></h4>

<p>Anmol and Puneet Jaggi held leadership roles in both <strong>BluSmart</strong> and <strong>Gensol</strong>. This dual control allowed them to shift funds and assets across entities without independent checks. While Gensol was meant to procure and lease EVs to BluSmart, the actual disbursement and usage of funds were poorly documented.</p>

<a name="L2.--3c-strong-3e-Falsified-Board-Resolutions-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>2. <strong>Falsified Board Resolutions</strong></h4>

<p>SEBI’s investigation revealed that board resolutions submitted to justify fund transfers from Gensol to other entities were <strong>forged</strong>. These resolutions claimed shareholder or board approvals that never took place.</p>

<a name="L3.--3c-strong-3e-Diversion-of-Funds-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>3. <strong>Diversion of Funds</strong></h4>

<p>Out of the ₹978 crore loan sanctioned to Gensol for 6,400 EVs:</p>

<ul>
<li>Only <strong>4,704 EVs</strong> were procured.</li>
<li>Over <strong>₹262 crore</strong> could not be accounted for.</li>
<li><p>Some funds were redirected to purchase <strong>personal assets</strong>, including:</p>

<ul>
<li>A ₹50 crore luxury apartment at DLF Camellias, Gurugram</li>
<li>Golf equipment worth ₹26 lakh</li>
<li>Foreign trips and personal company expenses</li>
<li>Transfers to family members and promoter-controlled entities</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<a name="L4.--3c-strong-3e-Blurring-the-Lines-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>4. <strong>Blurring the Lines</strong></h4>

<p>Because Gensol was the lender-facing entity and BluSmart was the consumer-facing app, the two were treated as distinct. However, in reality, the same core leadership ran both. This lack of separation allowed for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Overreporting of assets</li>
<li>Misleading investor communications</li>
<li>Obscuring of fund flows between listed and private companies</li>
</ul>


<a name="L5.--3c-strong-3e-Impact-on-Public-Markets-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h4>5. <strong>Impact on Public Markets</strong></h4>

<p>Gensol Engineering’s stock plummeted over 85% following SEBI&rsquo;s interim order. Investors who trusted the company’s renewable energy mission were blindsided by its role in enabling a startup’s financial misconduct.</p>

<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Timeline-of-Events-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Timeline of Events</strong></h3>

<div class="timeline-container">
  <div class="timeline">
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">2019</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">BluSmart founded by Anmol and Puneet Jaggi</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">2021–2024</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">₹978 crore disbursed to Gensol for EV procurement</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">April 15, 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">SEBI interim order reveals ₹262 crore fund diversion via Gensol</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">April 17, 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">BluSmart halts operations across all cities</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">May 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">Grant Thornton appointed for forensic audit of Gensol and BluSmart</div>
    </div>
    <div class="timeline-event">
      <div class="timeline-date">June 2025</div>
      <div class="timeline-content">Delhi High Court orders seizure of over 700 EVs leased by Gensol to BluSmart</div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>




<style>
.timeline-container {
  max-width: 1000px;
  margin: 10px auto;
  padding: 20px;
  font-family: &#8216;Segoe UI&#8217;, sans-serif;
}

.timeline {
  display: flex;
  flex-wrap: wrap;
  justify-content: space-between;
  border-left: 4px solid #049CDB;
  padding-left: 20px;
  position: relative;
}

.timeline-event {
  position: relative;
  width: 100%;
  margin-bottom: 30px;
  padding-left: 20px;
}

.timeline-event::before {
  content: &#8221;;
  position: absolute;
  left: -12px;
  top: 8px;
  background-color: #049CDB;
  border: 3px solid white;
  border-radius: 50%;
  height: 16px;
  width: 16px;
  z-index: 1;
}

.timeline-date {
  font-weight: bold;
  font-size: 16px;
  color: #049CDB;
  margin-bottom: 5px;
}

.timeline-content {
  background: #f8f9fa;
  padding: 12px 16px;
  border-left: 4px solid #049CDB;
  border-radius: 6px;
  box-shadow: 0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,0.05);
}
</style>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Consequences-of-the-Scam-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Consequences of the Scam</strong></h3>

<p><strong>Investors and Markets</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Gensol’s credibility as a listed renewable energy company is under threat.</li>
<li>Public lenders like PFC and IREDA face scrutiny for failing to detect misuse earlier.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Regulatory Oversight</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SEBI’s action has prompted tighter surveillance of related-party transactions in startups.</li>
<li>The Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA) is reviewing whether more stringent cross-holding disclosures are required for startups using public debt.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Drivers and Users</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Over 10,000 drivers, mostly from underserved backgrounds, lost income overnight.</li>
<li>BluSmart customers are still awaiting wallet refunds or app updates.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Future of BluSmart</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Talks of reviving the company via an independent board or acquisition have emerged.</li>
<li>Some investors, including BP Ventures, may pursue legal action to recover their equity.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Lessons-from-Gensol-e2--80--93-BluSmart-Case-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Lessons from Gensol–BluSmart Case</strong></h3>

<div class="lessons-section">
  <div class="lessons-grid">
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Dual Leadership in Public/Private Firms</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Strong boundaries between promoter-led entities are essential.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Lack of Board Independence</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Board members should be empowered to question and audit all fund movements.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Weak Internal Controls</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Statutory audits must detect and flag multi-crore diversions early.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="lesson-card">
      <h3 class="issue-title">Misuse of Public Money</h3>
      <p class="lesson-text">Lending institutions need better tracking for disbursed capital.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>




<style>
.lessons-section {
  max-width: 1100px;
  margin: 10px auto;
  padding: 20px;
  font-family: &#8216;Segoe UI&#8217;, sans-serif;
}


.lessons-grid {
  display: grid;
  grid-template-columns: repeat(auto-fit, minmax(260px, 1fr));
  gap: 20px;
}

.lesson-card {
  border-left: 5px solid #049CDB;
  padding: 20px;
  border-radius: 8px;
  box-shadow: 0 2px 6px rgba(0,0,0,0.08);
  transition: transform 0.2s;
}

.lesson-card:hover {
  transform: translateY(-4px);
}

.issue-title {
  font-size: 18px;
  font-weight: bold;
  color: #049CDB;
  margin-bottom: 10px;
}

.lesson-text {
  font-size: 16px;
  color: #444;
  line-height: 1.5;
}
</style>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Conclusion-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>

<p>The BluSmart-Gensol scandal underscores a critical truth: governance is not optional. Innovation, sustainability, and market expansion are meaningless if built on opaque finances and related-party secrecy.</p>

<p>Gensol’s role in the BluSmart collapse shows how a listed company can be used as a conduit for private ambition if oversight is weak. As India’s startup ecosystem matures, this case should serve as a clear signal — accountability must scale along with vision.</p>

<p>BluSmart’s fall was not due to a lack of market demand or poor technology. It failed because of misaligned ethics, enabled by a public company that chose opacity over integrity.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[FTX Scandal 2023: Timeline, Facts, and Key Players]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/ftx-scandal-2023-timeline/"/>
        <updated>2025-06-14T13:49:37+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/ftx-scandal-2023-timeline</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the annals of modern financial history, few names have sparked as much controversy, disbelief, and chaos as <em>Futures Exchange (FTX)</em>. Once hailed as a shining star of the cryptocurrency world, FTX’s meteoric rise and catastrophic fall stunned investors, regulators, and the general public alike. By the end of 2023, the scandal surrounding FTX and its founder Sam Bankman-Fried had cemented its place as one of the largest and most complex financial frauds of the 21st century.</p>

<p>This blog dives into the rise and fall of FTX, examining the events that led to its collapse, the financial and human toll it took, and the key takeaways from a debacle that shook the entire crypto industry to its core.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/ftx.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Rise-of-FTX:-From-Start-2d-up-to-Crypto-Juggernaut"></a>
<h3>The Rise of FTX: From Start-up to Crypto Juggernaut</h3>

<p>FTX was founded in 2019 by Sam Bankman-Fried (commonly referred to as SBF), a former Wall Street quant with a background from MIT and a reputation for genius-level intellect. The exchange was created as a more sophisticated platform for cryptocurrency derivatives and quickly attracted traders looking for advanced features, high leverage, and innovative products.</p>

<p>By 2021, FTX had:</p>

<ul>
<li>Raised over <strong>\$1.8 billion</strong> from prominent investors including Sequoia Capital, SoftBank, and Tiger Global.</li>
<li>Claimed <strong>over 1 million users</strong> and processed billions of dollars in trades daily.</li>
<li>Achieved a staggering <strong>\$32 billion valuation</strong>, making it the <strong>third-largest crypto exchange</strong> globally.</li>
</ul>


<p>SBF’s influence extended well beyond the company. He was a frequent guest on financial talk shows, lobbied in Washington, and was dubbed the “JP Morgan of crypto” after bailing out other struggling crypto firms in 2022. But behind the charismatic image and philanthropic posturing was a house of cards waiting to collapse.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="/images/2025/ftx_revenue.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Fall-Begins:-A-Leak-2c--a-Tweet-2c--and-a-Run-on-the-Bank"></a>
<h3>The Fall Begins: A Leak, a Tweet, and a Run on the Bank</h3>

<p>The trigger came in <strong>early November 2022</strong>, when <em>CoinDesk</em> published a leaked balance sheet from Alameda Research, a trading firm closely tied to FTX and also founded by SBF. The leak revealed that:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>\$5.8 billion</strong> of Alameda’s assets were in <strong>FTT</strong>, the native token issued by FTX.</li>
<li>A large portion of Alameda&rsquo;s balance sheet was illiquid and backed by FTT, suggesting FTX and Alameda were dangerously intertwined.</li>
</ul>


<p>This revelation sparked panic in the market. <strong>Binance</strong>, FTX’s main rival, announced it would liquidate its <strong>\$530 million</strong> worth of FTT holdings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/FTX_token_price.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<p>What followed was a textbook “run on the bank.” Within <strong>72 hours</strong>, FTX customers tried to withdraw <strong>\$6 billion</strong>, exposing the exchange’s inability to meet withdrawal demands. On <strong>November 11, 2022</strong>, FTX, Alameda Research, and over 130 related entities filed for bankruptcy.</p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Aftermath:-Bankruptcy-2c--Arrests-2c--and-a-Trial"></a>
<h3>The Aftermath: Bankruptcy, Arrests, and a Trial</h3>

<p>The bankruptcy filings laid bare the chaos within FTX:</p>

<ul>
<li>An estimated <strong>\$8–10 billion</strong> in customer funds were <strong>missing</strong>.</li>
<li>FTX had <strong>no proper financial records</strong>, and assets were reportedly tracked in <strong>QuickBooks</strong>, a tool meant for small businesses.</li>
<li>The new CEO, <strong>John J. Ray III</strong> (who previously oversaw Enron’s liquidation), called FTX&rsquo;s management the worst he’d seen in his 40-year career.</li>
</ul>


<p>In <strong>December 2022</strong>, SBF was arrested in the Bahamas and extradited to the U.S. He was charged with <strong>eight counts</strong> of fraud, money laundering, and campaign finance violations.</p>

<p>During the 2023 trial:</p>

<ul>
<li>Testimonies from former FTX executives (including Caroline Ellison, CEO of Alameda and SBF’s former girlfriend) revealed deliberate misappropriation of customer funds.</li>
<li>Prosecutors showed that billions were siphoned from FTX to fund Alameda’s risky bets, luxury real estate, political donations (over <strong>\$90 million</strong>), and personal expenses.</li>
</ul>


<p>In <strong>November 2023</strong>, Sam Bankman-Fried was found <strong>guilty on all counts</strong>, facing a potential sentence of over <strong>110 years</strong> in prison. His sentencing is scheduled for <strong>March 2024</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<a name="The-Numbers-That-Define-the-Collapse"></a>
<h3>The Numbers That Define the Collapse</h3>

<style>
  .ftx-table {
    width: 100%;
    border-collapse: collapse;
    margin: 20px 0;
    font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 16px;
  }

  .ftx-table th, .ftx-table td {
    border: 1px solid #ddd;
    padding: 12px 16px;
    text-align: left;
  }

  .ftx-table th {
    background-color: #f4f4f4;
    font-weight: bold;
  }

  .ftx-table tr:nth-child(even) {
    background-color: #f9f9f9;
  }

  .ftx-table tr:hover {
    background-color: #f1f1f1;
  }
</style>




<table class="ftx-table">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Metric</th>
      <th>Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Peak Valuation of FTX</td>
      <td>$32 billion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Customer Funds Missing</td>
      <td>~$8–10 billion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Number of Users Affected</td>
      <td>Over 1 million</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Political Donations by SBF</td>
      <td>$90 million+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Real Estate Purchases</td>
      <td>$300 million+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Alameda Loan to SBF</td>
      <td>$1 billion+</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Legal and Bankruptcy Costs</td>
      <td>Estimated $200 million+</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>


<hr />

<a name="Broader-Impact-on-Crypto-and-Beyond"></a>
<h3>Broader Impact on Crypto and Beyond</h3>

<p>FTX’s collapse sent shockwaves through the crypto ecosystem:</p>

<ul>
<li>Prices of major cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum dropped over <strong>20%</strong> in the weeks following the collapse.</li>
<li>Several crypto lending platforms and hedge funds with FTX exposure, including <strong>Genesis</strong> and <strong>BlockFi</strong>, filed for bankruptcy.</li>
<li>Investors lost trust in centralized exchanges, pushing many toward <strong>cold wallets</strong> and <strong>DeFi platforms</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Regulators responded swiftly:</p>

<ul>
<li>U.S. Congress held hearings on crypto regulation.</li>
<li>The SEC and CFTC vowed tighter oversight of crypto platforms.</li>
<li>Discussions began around creating a federal framework for <strong>crypto custodianship</strong> and <strong>proof-of-reserves</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Lessons-from-the-FTX-Scandal"></a>
<h3>Lessons from the FTX Scandal</h3>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Charisma is not competence</strong>
SBF’s charm, intelligence, and philanthropic front masked serious mismanagement and fraudulent practices.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Regulatory gaps need closing</strong>
FTX operated in a regulatory gray zone, exploiting jurisdictional loopholes to avoid scrutiny.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Centralization without accountability is dangerous</strong>
Despite being a crypto exchange, FTX was run like a black box. There were no independent board members or external audits.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Always follow the money</strong>
The FTX saga revealed the ease with which customer funds could be co-mingled and misused in the absence of checks and balances.</p></li>
</ol>


<hr />

<a name="Final-Thoughts"></a>
<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>

<p>FTX was not just a crypto story—it was a human story of unchecked power, blind trust, and systemic failure. It shook investor confidence and became a harsh reminder that, even in the futuristic world of blockchain, age-old rules of governance, transparency, and ethics cannot be ignored.</p>

<p>As the crypto industry tries to rebuild in the wake of this collapse, FTX will stand as a cautionary tale—a reminder that even billion-dollar empires can crumble when built on deception.</p>

<p>Let this not just be history, but a lesson for the future.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coca-Cola: A Legacy of Success, Controversy, and Resilience]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/coca-cola-a-legacy-of-success/"/>
        <updated>2025-03-09T21:07:15+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/coca-cola-a-legacy-of-success</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Coca-Cola is one of the most iconic brands in the world, with a history spanning over a century. It has become synonymous with soft drinks, creating a massive global presence. This case study explores Coca-Cola’s success story, key crises, and scandals, as well as how the company has managed to remain a market leader for so long.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/coca_cola.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="The-Success-Story"></a>
<h2>The Success Story</h2>

<a name="Origins-and-Early-Growth"></a>
<h3>Origins and Early Growth</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola was invented in 1886 by Dr. John Stith Pemberton in Atlanta, Georgia.</li>
<li>The formula was later bought by Asa Candler, who aggressively marketed it and expanded distribution.</li>
<li>By 1895, Coca-Cola was sold across the United States.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Market-Domination"></a>
<h3>Market Domination</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola became a household name through <strong>branding, advertising, and distribution</strong>.</li>
<li>By 1919, the company was sold to a group of investors for <strong>$25 million</strong>.</li>
<li>The introduction of the iconic <strong>contour bottle in 1915</strong> helped distinguish Coca-Cola from competitors.</li>
<li>The company’s famous Santa Claus campaign in the 1930s reinforced its association with happiness and celebration.</li>
<li>By the 1950s, Coca-Cola had expanded into more than <strong>100 countries</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<a name="Product-Diversification"></a>
<h3>Product Diversification</h3>

<ul>
<li>In response to changing consumer preferences, Coca-Cola introduced products such as <strong>Diet Coke (1982), Coca-Cola Zero (2005), and Coca-Cola Life (2013)</strong>.</li>
<li>The company expanded into other beverage categories, acquiring <strong>Minute Maid (1960), Dasani (1999), and Costa Coffee (2018)</strong>.</li>
<li>Today, Coca-Cola owns over <strong>500 brands</strong> across more than <strong>200 countries</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Financial-Strength"></a>
<h3>Financial Strength</h3>

<ul>
<li>As of 2023, Coca-Cola’s annual revenue was <strong>$43 billion</strong>.</li>
<li>It holds a global market share of <strong>nearly 50%</strong> in the carbonated soft drinks industry.</li>
<li>The company spends <strong>over $4 billion annually</strong> on marketing and advertising.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Key-Facts--26-amp-3b--Figures"></a>
<h3>Key Facts &amp; Figures</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Founded:</strong> 1886</li>
<li><strong>Annual Revenue (2023):</strong> $43 billion</li>
<li><strong>Number of Countries Operated In:</strong> 200+</li>
<li><strong>Brands Owned:</strong> 500+</li>
<li><strong>Global Market Share (Soft Drinks):</strong> ~50%</li>
<li><strong>Annual Advertising Spend:</strong> $4 billion+</li>
<li><strong>Employees:</strong> 79,000+</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Major-Crises-and-Scandals"></a>
<h2>Major Crises and Scandals</h2>

<a name="The--22-New-Coke-22--Disaster--28-1985-29-"></a>
<h3>The &ldquo;New Coke&rdquo; Disaster (1985)</h3>

<ul>
<li>In 1985, Coca-Cola reformulated its flagship product, replacing it with &ldquo;New Coke.&rdquo;</li>
<li>The change sparked widespread backlash, with over <strong>400,000 complaints</strong> from customers.</li>
<li>Coca-Cola reintroduced the original formula as &ldquo;Coca-Cola Classic&rdquo; within <strong>79 days</strong>, turning the fiasco into a marketing triumph.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/new_coke.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Racial-Discrimination-Lawsuit--28-1999-29-"></a>
<h3>Racial Discrimination Lawsuit (1999)</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola faced a <strong>$192.5 million settlement</strong> after being sued for racial discrimination in hiring and promotions.</li>
<li>The lawsuit led to significant changes in the company’s diversity and inclusion policies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="India-Pesticide-Controversy--28-2003-2d-2006-29-"></a>
<h3>India Pesticide Controversy (2003-2006)</h3>

<ul>
<li>A study in India found that Coca-Cola products contained pesticide residues <strong>24 times above European standards</strong>.</li>
<li>Sales dropped significantly in India, leading to factory closures and government scrutiny.</li>
<li>Coca-Cola later invested in <strong>water conservation projects</strong> and sustainability efforts to repair its image.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Water-Usage--26-amp-3b--Environmental-Concerns"></a>
<h3>Water Usage &amp; Environmental Concerns</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola has faced criticism over excessive water usage, particularly in water-scarce regions.</li>
<li>In 2007, it pledged to become <strong>water neutral by 2020</strong>, a goal it claims to have met by replenishing <strong>100% of the water used</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Coca-2d-Cola-and-Health-Concerns"></a>
<h3>Coca-Cola and Health Concerns</h3>

<ul>
<li>The company has been accused of contributing to the global obesity crisis.</li>
<li>In 2015, reports emerged that Coca-Cola funded research downplaying the role of sugary drinks in obesity.</li>
<li>In response, Coca-Cola introduced <strong>low-sugar and no-sugar options</strong> and expanded its portfolio to include healthier beverages.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="Strategies-for-Long-2d-Term-Success"></a>
<h2>Strategies for Long-Term Success</h2>

<a name="Strong-Branding--26-amp-3b--Marketing"></a>
<h3>Strong Branding &amp; Marketing</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola’s brand is valued at <strong>over $89 billion</strong>, making it one of the most recognized in the world.</li>
<li>The &ldquo;Share a Coke&rdquo; campaign (2011) personalized bottles, driving a <strong>2% increase in sales</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Global-Expansion--26-amp-3b--Localization"></a>
<h3>Global Expansion &amp; Localization</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola adapts its products to regional tastes. In Japan, for instance, it sells <strong>green tea and coffee variants</strong>.</li>
<li>It has established a vast distribution network, ensuring availability in <strong>even the most remote areas</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Innovation--26-amp-3b--Product-Adaptation"></a>
<h3>Innovation &amp; Product Adaptation</h3>

<ul>
<li>The company has continuously introduced new beverages, including <strong>plant-based and functional drinks</strong>.</li>
<li>Investments in sustainability and health-focused products help maintain relevance in changing markets.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/coke_brands.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Crisis-Management--26-amp-3b--Adaptability"></a>
<h3>Crisis Management &amp; Adaptability</h3>

<ul>
<li>Coca-Cola’s ability to pivot quickly, such as during the &ldquo;New Coke&rdquo; crisis, has been key to maintaining customer trust.</li>
<li>Transparency and corporate social responsibility efforts have helped it recover from controversies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Coca-Cola’s longevity can be attributed to <strong>strong branding, global expansion, adaptability, and crisis management</strong>. Despite facing significant challenges, the company remains a market leader due to its ability to evolve and stay relevant in a changing world.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: The Collapse of Silicon Valley Bank]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-the-collapse-of-silicon-valley-bank/"/>
        <updated>2025-03-09T11:48:11+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-the-collapse-of-silicon-valley-bank</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Silicon Valley Bank (SVB) was one of the largest banks catering to the startup and venture capital ecosystem in the United States. Its sudden collapse in March 2023 sent shockwaves through the financial sector, prompting government intervention and raising concerns about the stability of other regional banks. This case study explores the factors that led to SVB&rsquo;s failure, its impact, and key lessons learned.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/svb.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Background-of-Silicon-Valley-Bank"></a>
<h2>Background of Silicon Valley Bank</h2>

<p>Founded in 1983, SVB grew into the 16th largest bank in the U.S., with assets exceeding $209 billion by the end of 2022. It specialized in serving technology startups, venture capital (VC) firms, and innovation-driven companies. SVB&rsquo;s business model relied heavily on deposit funding from these clients and investments in long-duration U.S. government bonds.</p>

<!--more-->


<a name="Growth-and-Success"></a>
<h3>Growth and Success</h3>

<ul>
<li>By 2021, SVB’s total assets grew by 215% compared to 2019.</li>
<li>It controlled nearly <strong>50% of all venture-backed startups’ deposits</strong> in the U.S.</li>
<li>A key player in the tech boom, SVB benefited from rising valuations, strong venture funding, and low interest rates.</li>
</ul>


<a name="The-Downfall:-Key-Factors-Leading-to-the-Collapse"></a>
<h2>The Downfall: Key Factors Leading to the Collapse</h2>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Overreliance-on-Long-2d-Term-Bonds-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Overreliance on Long-Term Bonds</strong></h3>

<p>SVB invested heavily in long-term U.S. Treasury bonds and mortgage-backed securities (MBS) to generate returns. However, these investments carried significant interest rate risk.</p>

<ul>
<li>By 2022, nearly <strong>57% of SVB’s total assets ($120 billion)</strong> were invested in securities, primarily long-duration bonds.</li>
<li>When interest rates rise, bond values fall, creating unrealized losses.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Federal-Reserve-e2--80--99-s-Interest-Rate-Hikes-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Federal Reserve’s Interest Rate Hikes</strong></h3>

<ul>
<li>The Federal Reserve raised interest rates <strong>11 times from March 2022 to March 2023</strong>, increasing the federal funds rate from <strong>0.25% to 4.75%</strong>.</li>
<li>The sharp rise in rates led to a <strong>$17 billion unrealized loss</strong> on SVB’s bond portfolio.</li>
<li>This devalued SVB’s assets, making it more vulnerable to liquidity pressures.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Tech-Industry-Slowdown-and-Deposit-Flight-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Tech Industry Slowdown and Deposit Flight</strong></h3>

<ul>
<li>As interest rates rose, venture capital funding declined <strong>by 31% in 2022</strong>, leading startups to withdraw deposits.</li>
<li>SVB’s deposits dropped from <strong>$198 billion in March 2022 to $165 billion by the end of 2022</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Panic-and-Bank-Run--28-March-2023-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Panic and Bank Run (March 2023)</strong></h3>

<ul>
<li>On <strong>March 8, 2023</strong>, SVB announced it had sold $21 billion worth of securities at a <strong>$1.8 billion loss</strong> and planned to raise $2.25 billion in new capital.</li>
<li>This triggered panic among VC firms and startups, leading to mass withdrawals of <strong>$42 billion in a single day</strong> (March 9).</li>
<li>On <strong>March 10, 2023</strong>, regulators shut down SVB, marking the <strong>largest U.S. bank failure since 2008</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<a name="Government-and-Market-Response"></a>
<h2>Government and Market Response</h2>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-FDIC-Intervention-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>FDIC Intervention</strong></h3>

<ul>
<li>The <strong>Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (FDIC)</strong> took control of SVB, ensuring deposits up to <strong>$250,000</strong>.</li>
<li>On <strong>March 12, 2023</strong>, the U.S. government guaranteed all deposits, preventing wider contagion.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Stock-Market-and-Banking-Sector-Impact-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Stock Market and Banking Sector Impact</strong></h3>

<ul>
<li>Bank stocks plummeted, with <strong>First Republic Bank losing 70%</strong> of its value within days.</li>
<li>The <strong>KBW Bank Index</strong> (measuring U.S. bank performance) dropped <strong>18% in March 2023</strong>.</li>
<li>Global financial markets reacted sharply, fearing systemic risks.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/svb_stock.avif" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="Key-Lessons-and-Takeaways"></a>
<h2>Key Lessons and Takeaways</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>The Risk of Asset-Liability Mismatch</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SVB’s heavy reliance on long-duration bonds while serving short-term depositors created a major mismatch, exposing
it to liquidity risk.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Interest Rate Sensitivity in Banking</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Banks must proactively hedge against interest rate fluctuations, especially in a rising-rate environment.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>The Power of Panic and Social Media</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SVB’s collapse was exacerbated by rapid digital bank runs, fueled by panic-driven withdrawals coordinated through
social media and VC networks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Regulatory and Risk Management Gaps</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SVB was exempt from <strong>Dodd-Frank stress testing</strong> due to relaxed regulations in 2018.</li>
<li>Stricter oversight on regional banks could have mitigated risks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<a name="Conclusion"></a>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The collapse of Silicon Valley Bank exposed vulnerabilities in the financial system, particularly for banks with concentrated deposit bases and interest rate exposure. While the FDIC’s intervention prevented a broader crisis, the incident underscored the need for robust risk management, diversified banking strategies, and stronger regulatory frameworks. SVB’s downfall serves as a cautionary tale for financial institutions navigating uncertain economic conditions.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: The Collapse of Credit Suisse]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-the-collapse-of-credit-suisse/"/>
        <updated>2025-03-09T11:28:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-the-collapse-of-credit-suisse</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Credit Suisse, one of Switzerland’s most prestigious banks, fell from grace due to years of scandals, mismanagement, and financial instability. Once a symbol of Swiss banking excellence, the bank collapsed in 2023, forcing a historic takeover by UBS. This case study explores the major factors leading to Credit Suisse’s downfall, examining key financial data, regulatory failures, and market reactions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/credit_suisse.webp" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Background-of-Credit-Suisse-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Background of Credit Suisse</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Founded</strong>: 1856</li>
<li><strong>Headquarters</strong>: Zurich, Switzerland</li>
<li><strong>Peak Market Capitalization</strong>: ~$96 billion (2007)</li>
<li><strong>Core Services</strong>: Investment banking, wealth management, asset management</li>
</ul>


<p>Credit Suisse was once among the most respected global banks, competing with giants like JPMorgan Chase, Goldman Sachs, and Deutsche Bank. However, a series of financial missteps and scandals weakened its standing in the banking industry.</p>

<!--more-->


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Key-Events-Leading-to-the-Collapse-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Key Events Leading to the Collapse</strong></h2>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Archegos-Capital-Collapse--28-2021-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Archegos Capital Collapse (2021)</strong></h3>

<p><strong>What Happened?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Archegos Capital, a highly leveraged hedge fund run by Bill Hwang, used complex financial instruments called <strong>total return swaps</strong> to take massive, concentrated positions in stocks like ViacomCBS.</li>
<li>When stock prices dropped, Archegos defaulted on margin calls, leading to <strong>$10 billion in combined losses</strong> across multiple banks.</li>
<li>Credit Suisse was <strong>the worst hit</strong>, losing <strong>$5.5 billion</strong>, compared to Nomura ($2 billion) and Goldman Sachs ($0 due to better risk management).</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Impact:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Immediate <strong>stock price drop of 14%</strong>.</li>
<li>Credit Suisse&rsquo;s <strong>Chief Risk Officer and Head of Investment Banking resigned</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Regulatory investigations</strong> into its risk oversight.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Greensill-Capital-Scandal--28-2021-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Greensill Capital Scandal (2021)</strong></h3>

<p><strong>What Happened?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Greensill Capital, a supply-chain finance firm, collapsed in March 2021 after losing investor confidence.</li>
<li>Credit Suisse had <strong>$10 billion in exposure</strong> through supply chain finance funds that Greensill managed.</li>
<li>Investigations revealed that Credit Suisse had <strong>overlooked high-risk loans</strong> tied to Greensill’s questionable business model.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Impact:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Credit Suisse was forced to <strong>freeze $10 billion in client funds</strong>.</li>
<li>Investors filed lawsuits for <strong>mismanagement and negligence</strong>.</li>
<li>Further <strong>damage to its reputation and regulatory scrutiny</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Money-Laundering-and-Legal-Issues-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Money Laundering and Legal Issues</strong></h3>

<p>Credit Suisse was repeatedly implicated in financial scandals:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>2022: Cocaine Trafficking Case</strong> – Swiss courts found Credit Suisse guilty of <strong>failing to prevent money laundering</strong> for a Bulgarian cocaine cartel.</li>
<li><strong>2014-2022: U.S. Tax Evasion Scandals</strong> – The bank paid over <strong>$2.6 billion in fines</strong> for helping wealthy clients evade U.S. taxes.</li>
<li><strong>Mozambique “Tuna Bonds” Scandal</strong> – Credit Suisse arranged <strong>fraudulent loans worth $2 billion</strong>, leading to a national debt crisis in Mozambique.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Impact:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Legal fines exceeding <strong>$5 billion</strong> over a decade.</li>
<li>Loss of investor and client confidence.</li>
<li>Declining reputation and regulatory pressure.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-2022-2d-2023-Liquidity-Crisis--26-amp-3b--Collapse-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>2022-2023 Liquidity Crisis &amp; Collapse</strong></h3>

<p><strong>What Happened?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>In <strong>October 2022</strong>, rumors spread about Credit Suisse’s financial instability.</li>
<li>Wealthy clients <strong>withdrew $120 billion</strong> in Q4 2022 alone.</li>
<li>The bank’s stock <strong>plunged 75% in 2022</strong>.</li>
<li>The collapse of <strong>Silicon Valley Bank (SVB) in March 2023</strong> triggered a broader banking crisis, intensifying fears about Credit Suisse.</li>
<li><strong>Saudi National Bank</strong>, Credit Suisse’s largest investor (9.9% stake), <strong>refused to inject more capital</strong>, worsening the crisis.</li>
<li>The Swiss government intervened, brokering a <strong>$3.2 billion emergency takeover by UBS</strong> in March 2023.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/cs_chart.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /><em>Source: Internet</em></p>

<p><strong>Market Reaction:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Credit Suisse stock hit an all-time low of $0.82 before the UBS takeover.</strong></li>
<li><strong>UBS share price surged</strong> as markets viewed the deal as a stabilization move.</li>
<li><strong>Swiss government guaranteed $9 billion in losses</strong> for UBS to absorb Credit Suisse’s assets.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Final-Collapse--26-amp-3b--UBS-Takeover-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Final Collapse &amp; UBS Takeover</strong></h2>

<p>On <strong>March 19, 2023</strong>, the Swiss government orchestrated a forced merger between UBS and Credit Suisse:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>UBS paid only $3.2 billion</strong>, a fraction of Credit Suisse’s former valuation.</li>
<li>Swiss authorities provided <strong>$100 billion in liquidity support</strong>.</li>
<li>The deal <strong>wiped out $17 billion in Credit Suisse&rsquo;s AT1 bonds</strong>, angering bondholders.</li>
<li>UBS’s market position strengthened, but <strong>thousands of jobs were cut</strong>.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Lessons-from-the-Credit-Suisse-Crisis-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Lessons from the Credit Suisse Crisis</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>The Importance of Strong Risk Management</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Credit Suisse’s exposure to <strong>highly leveraged entities (Archegos, Greensill)</strong> without proper risk controls was a
major factor in its downfall.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Reputation and Trust Are Everything in Banking</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Multiple scandals (money laundering, tax evasion, fraud) eroded public trust, leading to <strong>massive client withdrawals</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Government Intervention in Financial Crises</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Swiss regulators had to <strong>engineer an emergency UBS takeover</strong> to prevent systemic risk.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>The End of a Banking Giant</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>A <strong>167-year-old institution collapsed</strong> due to poor management, excessive risk-taking, and legal troubles.</li>
<li><strong>UBS now dominates Swiss banking</strong>, marking a shift in global finance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Conclusion-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>

<p>The Credit Suisse crisis serves as a cautionary tale for banks worldwide. Despite being a globally significant institution, its failure to manage risks, handle scandals, and maintain client confidence led to its <strong>historic collapse in 2023</strong>. With tighter regulations and increased scrutiny, the banking sector must learn from this failure to avoid similar downfalls in the future.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
