<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: case_study | Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/case-study/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2025-03-01T14:00:25+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Recession: A Tale of Boom]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/the-great-recession-a-tale-of-boom/"/>
        <updated>2025-02-28T21:37:56+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/the-great-recession-a-tale-of-boom</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Prologue:-The-Illusion-of-Prosperity-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Prologue: The Illusion of Prosperity</strong></h3>

<p>In the early 2000s, the United States and much of the Western world were riding high on a wave of economic prosperity. The stock market was booming, home prices were soaring, and credit was available to almost anyone who wanted it. The American Dream had never seemed more attainable. But beneath the surface, cracks were forming in the foundations of this seemingly unstoppable growth.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Act-1:-The-Bubble-Inflates--28-2000-2d-2006-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Act 1: The Bubble Inflates (2000-2006)</strong></h3>

<p>The origins of the Great Recession can be traced back to a combination of financial deregulation, a booming housing market, and risky lending practices.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The Role of Subprime Mortgages:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Banks and financial institutions, encouraged by deregulation, began issuing high-risk loans to borrowers with poor credit histories.</li>
<li>The subprime mortgage market grew from <strong>8% of total mortgage originations in 2001 to over 20% by 2006</strong>.</li>
<li>Mortgage-backed securities (MBS) and collateralized debt obligations (CDOs) turned these risky loans into attractive investments.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/subprime.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The Role of the Federal Reserve:</strong>

<ul>
<li>In response to the dot-com bubble burst in 2000, the Federal Reserve lowered interest rates from <strong>6.5% in 2000 to 1% by 2003</strong>.</li>
<li>Cheap credit fueled an artificial boom in housing, encouraging speculative investments.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<ul>
<li><strong>Wall Street’s Greed and Financial Engineering:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Major banks and financial institutions, including Lehman Brothers, Bear Stearns, and AIG, aggressively pushed for the sale of MBS and CDOs.</li>
<li>Credit rating agencies, such as Moody’s and Standard &amp; Poor’s, assigned AAA ratings to these risky securities, falsely signaling their safety to investors.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>By 2006, home prices had risen by <strong>188% from 1997 levels</strong>, creating a housing bubble of epic proportions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/real_estate.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Act-2:-The-Collapse-Begins--28-2007-2d-2008-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Act 2: The Collapse Begins (2007-2008)</strong></h3>

<p>The tipping point arrived in 2007 when homeowners began defaulting on their subprime mortgages. The housing market, once thought to be invincible, started crumbling.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/great_recession.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The First Domino Falls: Bear Stearns (March 2008)</strong>

<ul>
<li>Bear Stearns, a major investment bank, faced liquidity problems as its subprime-heavy hedge funds collapsed.</li>
<li>The Federal Reserve orchestrated its sale to JPMorgan Chase for <strong>just $2 per share</strong> (down from $172 a year earlier).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/bear_stearns.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Lehman Brothers: The Breaking Point (September 15, 2008)</strong>

<ul>
<li>Lehman Brothers, a 158-year-old financial giant, declared bankruptcy, marking the largest collapse in U.S. history with <strong>$639 billion in assets</strong>.</li>
<li>The Dow Jones Industrial Average plunged <strong>504 points in a single day</strong>, triggering panic in global markets.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/lehman_fall.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>AIG and the Federal Bailout (September 16, 2008)</strong>

<ul>
<li>American International Group (AIG), which had insured trillions in MBS through credit default swaps, faced insolvency.</li>
<li>The U.S. government stepped in with an <strong>$85 billion bailout</strong>, later expanding it to <strong>$182 billion</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/aig_2007.jpg" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Stock Market Collapse:</strong>

<ul>
<li>The S&amp;P 500 fell nearly <strong>57% from its peak in 2007 to its bottom in March 2009</strong>.</li>
<li>Unemployment soared from <strong>4.6% in 2007 to 10% by October 2009</strong>, with over <strong>8.7 million jobs lost</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/2025/stock_market_2007.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Act-3:-Global-Domino-Effect--28-2008-2d-2010-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Act 3: Global Domino Effect (2008-2010)</strong></h3>

<p>The crisis spread beyond the United States, leading to a worldwide recession.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Europe’s Banking Crisis:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Banks in the UK, Germany, and France faced massive losses due to exposure to U.S. mortgage securities.</li>
<li>Iceland’s banking system collapsed, forcing the government to seek a <strong>$4.6 billion bailout</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<ul>
<li><strong>China’s Response:</strong>

<ul>
<li>China launched a <strong>$586 billion stimulus package</strong>, investing in infrastructure and state-owned enterprises to
counter the slowdown.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<ul>
<li><strong>The Eurozone Debt Crisis:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Greece, Ireland, and Spain faced severe financial crises, requiring bailouts from the European Union and the International Monetary Fund (IMF).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Act-4:-Recovery-and-Reforms--28-2010-2d-Present-29--3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Act 4: Recovery and Reforms (2010-Present)</strong></h3>

<p>Governments around the world took aggressive steps to stabilize the economy.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The TARP Bailout (2008-2009):</strong>

<ul>
<li>The U.S. government introduced the <strong>$700 billion Troubled Asset Relief Program (TARP)</strong> to rescue failing banks.</li>
<li>Banks like Citigroup and Bank of America received significant funds, which were eventually repaid.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<ul>
<li><strong>Dodd-Frank Act (2010):</strong>

<ul>
<li>Introduced financial reforms, including the Volcker Rule, which restricted banks from engaging in risky investments.</li>
<li>Established the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB) to oversee lending practices.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<ul>
<li><strong>Slow but Steady Recovery:</strong>

<ul>
<li>The U.S. GDP contracted by <strong>4.3% during the recession</strong>, but recovered by 2013.</li>
<li>By 2018, unemployment had fallen to <strong>3.7%</strong>, and stock markets hit record highs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Epilogue:-Lessons-Learned-and-the-Road-Ahead-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h3><strong>Epilogue: Lessons Learned and the Road Ahead</strong></h3>

<p>The Great Recession reshaped the global financial landscape. It exposed the dangers of excessive risk-taking, inadequate regulation, and blind faith in financial engineering.</p>

<p>Lesser-known facts:</p>

<ul>
<li>Lehman Brothers’ failure was partially due to a refusal from Barclays and the UK government to intervene.</li>
<li>At the height of the crisis, the U.S. Federal Reserve secretly loaned over $16 trillion to global banks to prevent a total collapse.</li>
<li>Warren Buffett described the financial derivatives market as &ldquo;financial weapons of mass destruction&rdquo; years before the crisis hit.</li>
</ul>


<p>While economies have largely recovered, new risks such as corporate debt bubbles and geopolitical tensions continue to pose challenges. The Great Recession serves as a stark reminder that financial stability is never guaranteed.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Lipton – A Global Tea Powerhouse]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-lipton-a-global-tea-powerhouse/"/>
        <updated>2025-02-26T18:16:23+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/case-study-lipton-a-global-tea-powerhouse</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the bustling streets of Glasgow, Scotland, in the 1870s, a young, ambitious entrepreneur named Sir Thomas Lipton had a vision—to make tea, once a luxury for the elite, accessible to everyone. Little did he know that his dream would evolve into a global tea empire that would redefine the industry for generations to come.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2025/lipton_logo.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-The-Humble-Beginnings-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>The Humble Beginnings</strong></h2>

<p>Thomas Lipton, born in 1848 to Irish immigrant parents, was no stranger to hard work. At the age of 15, he sailed to the United States, where he took up various jobs, including working in a grocery store. Observing the efficiency of American retail operations, he returned to Scotland with a dream of revolutionizing the food trade.</p>

<p>In 1871, at the age of 23, Lipton opened his first grocery store in Glasgow. He marketed his store as offering “the best goods at the cheapest prices,” a philosophy that won the hearts of working-class families. His business grew rapidly, and by the 1880s, he owned over 300 stores across Britain. But Lipton was always thinking bigger.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="/images/2025/lipton.png" height="300" width="900" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Breaking-Into-the-Tea-Industry-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Breaking Into the Tea Industry</strong></h2>

<p>During the late 19th century, tea was an expensive luxury, controlled by middlemen who inflated prices. Lipton saw an opportunity. Rather than relying on suppliers, he decided to cut out the middlemen and source tea directly from plantations in Ceylon (modern-day Sri Lanka). He bought vast tea estates, ensuring quality control and reducing costs.</p>

<p>To market his tea, Lipton leveraged his exceptional promotional skills. He sponsored hot air balloon events, used colorful advertisements, and even hired elephants to parade through London’s streets carrying Lipton Tea chests. His genius lay in making tea not just affordable but desirable.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Tea-for-the-Masses-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Tea for the Masses</strong></h2>

<p>Lipton introduced the concept of pre-packaged tea, a revolutionary idea at the time. Until then, tea was sold loose, and quality varied. By branding and packaging his tea, he guaranteed consistency, making it more appealing to customers. His slogan, “Direct from the Tea Gardens to the Teapot,” became synonymous with freshness and affordability.</p>

<p>By 1890, Lipton Tea was a household name in Britain, and soon, it spread across Europe and America. He even earned a royal warrant as the official tea supplier to Queen Victoria—a remarkable feat for a man who started with a single grocery store.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Global-Expansion-and-Innovations-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Global Expansion and Innovations</strong></h2>

<p>In the early 20th century, Lipton continued expanding, setting up distribution channels worldwide. One of the most significant milestones came in the 1950s when Lipton became part of the Unilever conglomerate, giving it access to unparalleled resources and global reach.</p>

<p>As consumer habits evolved, Lipton adapted. The introduction of tea bags in the 1950s and ready-to-drink iced tea in the 1990s revolutionized the industry. Lipton embraced health-conscious trends, launching green teas, herbal infusions, and organic blends.</p>

<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-Fun-Facts-and-Data-Points-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>Fun Facts and Data Points</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Lipton Today</strong>: Sold in over <strong>110 countries</strong>, Lipton is one of the world’s most recognizable tea brands.</li>
<li><strong>Tea Production</strong>: Lipton sources tea from <strong>more than 600 tea estates</strong> worldwide.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental Commitment</strong>: Lipton has committed to <strong>100% Rainforest Alliance Certified tea</strong>, ensuring sustainable farming practices.</li>
<li><strong>Marketing Genius</strong>: In 1929, Lipton launched one of the first-ever radio commercials in America, setting the stage for modern advertising strategies.</li>
</ul>


<a name="L-3c-strong-3e-The-Legacy-of-Lipton-3c--2f-strong-3e-"></a>
<h2><strong>The Legacy of Lipton</strong></h2>

<p>From a single grocery store in Glasgow to a global powerhouse, Lipton’s journey is a testament to innovation, persistence, and an unyielding belief in making quality tea accessible to all. Sir Thomas Lipton’s legacy endures not just in every cup of Lipton tea enjoyed worldwide but in the very fabric of modern retail and branding strategies.</p>

<p>So, the next time you sip on a warm cup of Lipton tea, remember—you’re not just drinking tea; you’re tasting a rich history steeped in vision and ingenuity.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
