<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: linux | Rishijeet Mishra]]></title>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2024-05-24T23:39:29+05:30</updated>
    <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Rishijeet Mishra]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[rishijeet@gmail.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Microsoft biased towards Linux]]></title>
        <link href="https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/is-microsoft-biased-towards-linux/"/>
        <updated>2016-03-11T09:45:09+05:30</updated>
        <id>https://rishijeet.github.io/blog/is-microsoft-biased-towards-linux</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I see news about Microsoft crafted a switch OS on Debian Linux platform,  announcing its SQL server of Linux and may be some more. Though this is a surprising news as Microsoft windows has released its best OS so far, which is more stable and fast compare to its ancestors, so what could be the reason to move towards Linux is a question. Is this related to the security aspect of the operating system or is it the open source nature of the platform and the community support it has or is it just the recent decision to move towards it ? Whatever it is, I see this as a strong move towards making its environment and platform more robust and performant.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>According to the Microsoft&rsquo;s Blog</p>

<p><i>
These improvements, and many more, are all built into SQL Server and bring you not just a new database but a complete platform for data management, business analytics and intelligent apps – one that can be used in a consistent way across both on-premises and the cloud. In fact, over the last year we’ve been using the SQL Server 2016 code-base to run in production more than 1.4 million SQL Databases in the cloud using our Azure SQL Database as a Service offering, and this real-world experience has made SQL Server 2016 an incredibly robust and battle-hardened data platform.
</i></p>


<p>
As the executive tells the New York Times, this is all about &#8220;market expansion.&#8221; Microsoft would rather corner the server software space, which has been shifting toward Linux, than insist on a Windows-only policy out of stubborn pride. It&#8217;s tough to know if the Linux server crowd will warm up to its longtime arch-rival, but those more open-minded firms are now free to integrate Microsoft without making a wholesale switch.
</p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
